(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-09T16:40:08.099286",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
そぷそぴ、そぴ！
Sopu-sopi, sopi!
いきます！うちら！
Here we go! Us!
遊び回りたーい！
Want to go play around!
はい、ということで始まりました！クイズ イグノーベル賞ウィズ遊び回りタイ！
Yes, and so it has begun! Quiz Ig Nobel Prize with Want to Play Around!
ということでみんなで盛り上がっていきましょう、イエーイ！
So let's get hyped together, yay!
はい、ではでは、本日クイズマスターを務めさせていただきます、遊び回りタイヒラメキ担当バーチャルサイエンスアイドル、スナシナ・ソピアです！
Today serving as your quiz master, I am the inspiration-in-charge virtual science idol of Want to Play Around, Sunashina Sopia!
そしてクイズに挑戦してくれるのが、今日もフルパワーでパトロール開始！ホロライブ遊び回りタイ最強担当のヒーローポリス、客堂きょうこ！
And taking on the quiz today, starting patrol with full power! From Want to Play Around's strongest division, Hakutou Kyouko!
あらあらめらめら、あちちーんめら！ホロライブ遊び回りタイごり押し担当の引瀬夜マンダ、あちちーんメロンなんだっちゃー！
My, my, burning up, hot-hot-melon! From Want to Play Around's brute-force division, Hikeshiya Manda!
そんでもってあなたに届け、ホロライブ遊び回りタイ癒やし担当の鈴奈ずずりです！
And reaching out to you, from Want to Play Around's healing division, Suzuna Zuzuri!
よろしくお願いします！
Nice to meet you!
よろしくお願いしまーす！ということで、このね遊び回りタイの4人でやっていきたいと思うんですけど、じゃあ早速ですね、今日の企画の紹介の方させていただこうと思います。
Nice to meet you! So, we'll be doing this with the four members, and I'd like to introduce today's project right away.
はい、みなさ…あ、ありがと…あと、なんかの音量のバランスとか、なんかあったらみなさん教えてくださいね。本当にみんな来てくれてありがとー！
Yes, everyone... ah, thank you... Also, please let us know if there's any issue with the volume balance. Thanks everyone for coming!
はーい、ではでは、本日クイズの企画なんですが、改めてクイズ イグノーベル賞ということで、
Right, so for today's project, once again, Quiz Ig Nobel Prize,
ま、クイズ番組をね、やっていきたいんですけれど、皆さん、イグノーベル賞ってご存知ですか？
we want to do a quiz show, but everyone, do you know what the Ig Nobel Prize is?
この前教えてもらったソピアに！お！うん！前聞いた！うん！
Sopia taught us before! Oh! Yeah! Heard it before! Yeah!
ということで、じゃあちょっと改めてね、はい、あの、皆さん、ノーベル賞ね、聞いたことある方多いと思うんですけれど、
So let's go over it again, yes, um, many of you have probably heard of the Nobel Prize,
ま、ちょうどね、あの、今ノーベル賞の発表シーズンでね、あの、今日も確か平和賞かな、の発表があったんですけれど、はい、ノーベル賞は人類にね、最大の貢献をもたらした者に与えられる本当に名誉ある賞なんですが、
well, right now is the Nobel Prize announcement season, and today I think the Peace Prize was announced, yes, the Nobel Prize is a truly prestigious award given to those who brought the greatest contributions to humanity,
ま、そのね、ノーベル賞のパロディ賞がイグノーベル賞。
and, well, the parody of that Nobel Prize is the Ig Nobel Prize.
人々を笑わせ、そして考えさせるような、驚くべき功績に対して与えられる賞となっております。
It is an award given for remarkable achievements that make people laugh and then make them think.
はい、じゃあ、これだけだとね、ちょっと分かりづらいかなって思うので、具体的にちょっと、過去のね、イグノーベル賞の受賞研究を2つほど、はい、紹介させていただこうと思います。
Yes, so if it's just this, it might be a bit hard to understand, so I'd like to introduce about two past Ig Nobel Prize-winning research projects specifically.
はい、じゃあ1つ目は、こちら！はい、こちら2014年のノーベル…あ、ノーベルじゃ、あ、イグノーベルです。
Yes, so the first one is here! Yes, here is the 2014 Nobel... ah, not Nobel, ah, Ig Nobel.
あ、イグノーベルもつけ、確証でい。ああ、今日ノーポンで行こうと思ってたのに、すいませーん。
Ah, I made it Ig Nobel too. Ah, I was planning to go with no-pon today, sorry.
もうダメだ、もうおしまいだ。はい、イグノーベル賞ですね、2014年イグノーベル物理学賞なんですけれど、
It's no good, it's over. Yes, the Ig Nobel Prize, the 2014 Ig Nobel Prize in Physics,
え、こちら、バナナの皮が滑る理由について、あの、ガチでマジメに摩擦の量とかを測定した研究に与えられました。
uh, for this, regarding why banana peels are slippery, it was awarded to research that seriously and genuinely measured the amount of friction and such.
え、すごっ！おお、マジメに？
Eh, amazing! Oh, seriously?
そうそうそう、本当にマジメに研究されてる方が、その、バナナってね、人が踏んだらさ、めっちゃ滑るじゃんっていうのを、
That's right, researchers really seriously studied how bananas, you know, when someone steps on them, they're super slippery,
ガチでその物理学的に、なんでこのバナナの皮は滑るんやってのを、ガチで真剣に研究したっていうところで、
and genuinely, physically, why banana peels are slippery, they seriously researched it, so...
まあ、本当に、その、もうね、あの、カードゲームとかやってるとさ、バナナめっちゃ滑るけど、あれなんでやねんってのを本気で、
Well, really, when you're playing card games and stuff, bananas are super slippery, why is that, they seriously
その、その、成分が入っていることで、みたいな、そういうやつってこと？
like, because those components are included, that kind of thing?
そうそうそうそう、そういうのをね、真剣に、そう、研究された…
Right, right, right, they seriously researched things like that...
はリサーチして 皆さんに改めてお伝えしようと思います。
research and present it to you all again.
その話で1時間ちょっと使ってほしいかもしれない。
That topic alone could take an hour, you know?
え、ね！本当に。
Right, right! Exactly!
1個深ボルトにそれだけでね、全然もう時間ね、すぐ経っちゃうから、ちょっと気になっちゃうもんで。
If we dig into just one, time will run out right away, so...
ねえ、ねえ。
Right? Right?
続いて2つ目。こちら！
Moving on to the second one. Here it is.
はい、これもイグノーベル物理学賞で。
This is also from the Ig Nobel Physics Prize.
そう、あのね昨日一昨日までずっとノーベル賞が頭ん中いっぱいであれちょっとイグをつけるの大変忘れちゃいました。不体裁すいません。
I completely forgot to attach "Ig" to it because I was thinking about the Nobel Prize all day yesterday and the day before.
はいこちら、2019イグノーベル物理学賞なんですけれど、
So, 2019 Ig Nobel Physics Prize, but...
はい、これ。ウォンバットのね、ちょっとあの今日この
Yeah, this is about wombats...
あ。
Ah.
見えちゃった！
It showed up!
あ、逆に隠しといてもらった方がよかったかな。YouTube君的には。
Actually, it would've been better to hide it for YouTube, content-wise.
でも、これくらいなら大丈夫だよねっていうことでね。あの、ウォンバットの皆さん、うんちって知ってる？
Well, this much is probably fine, right? Do you guys know what wombat poop is like?
うんち！アンチ！
Poop! Anti!
知らんない。
Who knows?
れおかんんな。
Reo-kan-na.
ウォンバットって、そう、サイコロ型のうんちするんですよ。
Wombats, yeah, they poop in cube shapes, you know.
ええ？みんな？
Eh? Everybody?
みんな、ウォンバットはみんな立方体のうんちするの。
Wombats all poop in cubic shapes?
え、しかも立方体、ちゃんと立方体なの？あ、ま、ちゃんと何ていうか、サイコロ型的な感じ？
And cube-shaped? Like, properly cube-shaped? Yeah, like cube-ish.
え、長方形じゃないんだ？
It's not rectangular?
あ、まったそう。あ、ま、厳密言うとね、あの、長方形かもしれないけど、
Ah, I see. Well, strictly speaking, it might be rectangular,
でもやっぱサイコロって例えられるくらいには立方体に近いやつ。
but you could compare it to a cube, it's pretty close to cubic.
確かに痛そうじゃん、つづり。
That sounds like it hurts... spelling it out.
めっちゃ痛そうじゃん、だって。確かに！
It sounds so painful, right? Exactly!
こんなね、角々してたらね、大変だよね。もう、ウォンバットちゃんのおしりの中ってどうなってるんだろうね、みたいな。
If they had corners like that all over, it'd be tough, you know? Like, I wonder what wombat poop teaching is like.
そう、それが研究に。そう、かもしかい、あの、一旦ね、そのフンをどうしてこんな立方体にできるのかみたいなことを研究された。
So, that was for research... Like, how the poop can become such a cubic shape, they researched that.
はい、研究者の方にイグ、イグノーベル物理学賞がね、与えられました。
Yes, the researchers were awarded the Ig Nobel Physics Prize.
なんでこれ、物理なん？
Why is this physics?
へえ？
Heh?
え、数学とかじゃないんだ？
It's not about math?
ね、これ。確かに。確かに。
Right? Exactly.
ただなんかやっぱその物理的な法則に基づいて、結局なんか、サイコロ型が一番ウォンバットてきにはみたいなの、たぶんそういう考察がされないいものかたち的な、かな？
Though it's based on physical laws, maybe they deduced that the cube shape is the most wombat-like shape.
おい、ちょっとこれもうね、私ね、リサーチしてまたソフィアの雑談とかでお話をしようと思うので、
Wait, let me research this more later and talk about it during Sophia's chat.
것도 1시간枠で！え、気になる！
This will take another hour!
はい、てな感じでね、ちょっとイグノーベル物理学賞過去の、どんな研究にね、与えられたかという、
Right, so that's how the past Ig Nobel Physics Prize research went.
これでちょっとだいたいなんか感じはつかめてきた。なんかイグノーベル賞ってどういう感じの研究に与えられるか的なところを
this gives you a rough idea of what kind of research gets an Ig Nobel Prize.
なんか、好きのやつだ。
Some people like it.
そう、ちょっとあの謎々とかクイズとか、なんか子どももわかる面白ナゼナゼネタみたいなのを、大人が大真面目に研究しましたみたいなやつ？
Yeah, adults seriously researched things like riddles, quizzes, and weird trivia that even kids would find funny, right?
そうそうそうそう、マジで。
That's right, that's right!
ええ？
Heh?
そう、やっぱさ、なんか真面質な研究者がさ、一番アホやってる時が一番面白くないかっていう、普段真面目な研究してる人たち。面白いもんね。
Yeah, when serious researchers act like fools, that's when it's most interesting, you know?
ねえ。
Neh?
ていうので、ま、今日はね、こういうイグノーベル賞から、特に2026年ちょうど先月9月にね、2026年のイグノーベル賞の発表があったので、
So today, we're taking inspiration from those Ig Nobel Prizes, and since the 2026 Ig Nobel Prizes were announced just last month in September,
今回は、はい、そこからね、ちょっと出題をさせていただこうと、思ってます。
we decided to create some quiz questions based on them!
最新だ！
First up!
そ、ほやほやの受賞したてほやほやの。
So, who won?
じゃあ、知らない人多いんじゃない？まだ。
So, a lot of people probably don't know yet, right?
おー！ていうのをね、ちょっと最新のイグノーベルに皆さんね、ぜひぜひ精通していただけたらっていうので、
"Oh?" We want everyone to get up to speed on the latest Ig Nobels!
ま、ぜひね、あのほんまにこんな研究あるんかいっていう、その驚きとね、面白さっていうのを、クイズを通して一緒に楽しんでいただけると嬉しいなって思います。
We want you to enjoy the surprise and fun of learning, "Wait, really, such research actually exists?!" through this quiz.
おっしゃあ！
Yay!
あ、ちなみにね、今回なんと豪華商品も、実は用意しちゃいます。
And by the way, we actually have gorgeous prizes for today!
豪華商品？
Gorgeous prizes?
何？何？何？
What? What?
お菓子！お菓子！お菓子！
Snacks! Snacks!
優勝者の人には、なんと
What are we giving the winner?
なんとなんと！10万ドルプレゼントします！
What? What? 100,000 dollars presented!
えっ！マジかよ！
Eh? Seriously?
お金、お金じゃお金、え、10万ドルってさ、
Money? Money? Dollars?
カバのスタジオより高い？
higher than Kana's studio?
あ、ちょうど高いか。
Is it higher?
あ、かも知れないね。
Ah, maybe?
え、カバのスタジオを買収してさ、遊び回り隊が選挙できる。
We can buy Kaba's studio and go around touring and campaigning!
え、社長になれるよ、うちらし。
Can we become presidents?
え、社長になれるの？
Can we become company presidents?
うん、経験取れるよ。
Yeah, you can get experience!
え、カブト、カブトとか全部買える？
Can we buy all the Kaba merch?
うん、余裕余裕。
Yeah, plenty!
マジかあ！
Awesome!
すごいよ。
Amazing!
遊び回り隊のっとる！のっとれ！のっとれ！
I wanna go tour and campaign! Catch 'em! Catch 'em!
のっとろ！うん。
Capture 'em!
下克上のじゃ、のっど！
Defeat them and take over!
あ、ね、ちょっと優勝者の人には本当ね、10万ドルガチでプレゼントしますので、皆さん頑張ってください！
So yeah, we'll genuinely present 100,000 dollars to the winner, so everyone do your best!
貯めたのかな、コツコツ。
Did they save it up? Piece by piece?
ねえ、ちょっとコツコツの間に、福祉号で貯めたんじゃない？
Yeah, saving it up in a piggy bank or something during the breaks?
えらい。
Awesome!
現実。ねえ、すごいのだあ！
Impressive! Right, that's amazing!
確かに。ソピアちょ、緊張んとしてそうじゃん。
True. Sophia's probably all nervous and stuff, right?
ねえ、確かに、もう経験でいいんだよ、ソピアは。
Right? She's saving up for it, Sophia is.
はい、じゃあね、えっと、いよいよ第1問いこうと思います！皆さん！
Alright, then, let's finally start Question 1! Everyone!
次 よろしいでしょうか。
Is everyone ready?
のっちゃ
Let's go!
ちなみにこのクイズはね、その、筆記で回答してもらおうと思ってるんですけれど
By the way, for this quiz, you'll be answering in writing...
ちょっとみんななんかすごい色々書いてくれてるんだがこれはあ、き、消えた。みらちゅん
Everyone is writing so many different things... Ah, it disappeared! Mirachun.
うん、ちゃんと。だってクイズするって言うから消したの
Yeah, properly. Because you said we're doing a quiz, I erased it.
待って待って待って、ちょっとツッコミたかったのに
Wait, wait, wait, I wanted to make a retort!
あ、準備してる？ちゃんと準備してる？
Ah, are you prepared? Are you properly prepared?
あ、ありがたい各か。あ、いいよいいよ。え、みらちゅんのあれだよね、
Ah, thank goodness. Ah, it's fine, it's fine. Mirachun's is that right,
ソフィアのこと書いてくれたんだよね。うん、根性。
you wrote about Sophia. Yeah, guts.
あ、ソフィの「根」は根性の「根」かなと思って書いてみたんだよ。
I thought Sophia's "ne" might stand for "neijou" (guts) and wrote that.
あ、なるほどね、根性ソフィアね。で、今日は「最強のきょうこ」書いてたって感じかな？
I see, Guts Sophia. And today you wrote "Strongest Kyoko", right?
うん、うん。で、え、つづりは何？お相撲さん？
Yeah, yeah. And, how do you spell it? Sumo wrestler?
ううん、違う、自己紹介してる。
No, wait, I'm introducing myself.
え、さっき、おねえさんを書いてたんだけど
Eh, earlier I wrote "Big Sister"...
え？さっきは何書いてたの？え、あれ、つづりだよ？
Eh? What were you writing earlier? Eh, that's the spelling, you know?
お相撲さん言われてたよ。
You were told you looked like a sumo wrestler!
なんでよ、つづりおねえさんねって、ちゃんと書いてたじゃん、プロポーズ書いてる人いる！
Why? I wrote "Tsuzuri-oneesan", didn't I? There's someone writing "proposal"!
ロマンチックなものがある。さらに輝く。さらに輝く、ロマンチックなものと言えば？
Something romantic. Shining even brighter. Speaking of something romantic that shines even brighter?
本ソフィ
Real Sophi.
はい、ていうこと で、じゃあね、こんな愉快なお遊びをしたいですけど、クイズはね、なんと10兆ドルかかってるんでね、
Right, so, we want to play around playfully like this, but since this quiz has a 10 trillion dollar prize on the line,
ちょっと真剣にね、取り組んでいただければ
we'd like you to take it seriously.
10兆ドルなんて、もう生きていけるやん！
10 trillion dollars means we can survive!
あれがあれば
If we have that,
ね、お菓子いっぱい買える絶対。
right, we can definitely buy so many snacks.
え、もしさ、この先めっちゃ長い気じゃけど、10兆ドルあったらさすがに何年きてもいけるよね。
Eh, even if the rest is super long, with 10 trillion dollars we can survive for however many years.
あ、全然！千年はいけるよ！千年は間違いなく。
Ah, totally! We can easily last a thousand years! Definitely a thousand years.
始まったのじゃ、はっ
It has started! Haha.
始まったな！ありがとうソフィア！
It has started! Thank you, Sophia!
いぇーい、じゃあ行きましょう、早速第1問。
Yay! Well then, let's go, right to Question 1.
じゃあちょっとね、みんなの回答は、あのみんなにはすぐには見れないようにするので、
So, everyone's answers won't be shown to everyone right away,
また回答の時に、はい、出して行こうと思います。
so we'll reveal them when it's time to answer.
じゃあ行きましょう、第1問！
Well then, let's go, Question 1!
ででん！
Ta-da!
あ、そういえばででんのを用意してたんだった。
Ah, come to think of it, I had prepared a "ta-da" sound effect.
もう一回、もう一回テイクして。いいよ、やってやって。
Take it again, take it again. It's fine, go ahead.
ででん！よし。
Ta-da! Alright.
今出たはず。
It should have appeared now.
みんなには聞こえてるはず。ごめん、うちらに聞こえないけど。
Everyone should be able to hear it. Sorry, we can't hear it.
でね、聞こえたよね？
You heard it, right?
うん。よし。
Yeah. Alright.
はい、ということで、えー第1問。2026年にイグノーベル技術賞を受賞した研究では
Right, so, Question 1: In 2026, research that won the Ig Nobel Technology Prize
とある生き物の体の一部を3Dプリンターのノズルとして利用しました。
used a part of a certain creature's body as a 3D printer nozzle.
何の生き物のどの部分でしょうか？
What creature's which body part was it?
ではでは、シンキングタイムスタート！
Now then, thinking time start!
ソフィア先生、質問のじゃあ
Sophia-sensei, about the question then
はい、なんでしょう？
Yes, what is it?
ノズルって何？
What's a nozzle?
ノズルっていうのはね、3Dプリンターって、みんな見たことあるかな？
A nozzle is... has everyone seen a 3D printer?
あるよ！ある！
I have! I have!
なんかね、あの3Dプリンターって、なんかそういう材料があって、それをなんかちょっと溶かして、
Like, a 3D printer has some material, melts it a bit,
それをね、その細いところからチュルチュルって出して、それを重ねていくことで立体物を作るんだけど、
and squeezes it out from a thin place like "churu-churu", and layers it to make 3D objects,
その本当の先端のその材料をチュルチュルって出すところ、の部分をノズルって言います。
but the very tip where the material comes out "churu-churu" is called a nozzle.
うん、なるほど。
Mm, I see.
なんか、ホイップの絞り口的な感じ？
Sort of like a whipped cream piping bag?
そうそうそうそう！まさにそう。ホイップっぽいやつか。
Exactly, exactly! Exactly like that. Something like whipped cream.
ホイップ口！
Piping tip!
ホイップっぽいやつか。
Something like whipped cream.
ひょっとして、ヒントかも知れない？
Could it be a hint?
大ヒントだ！
Major hint!
たしかに！
Indeed!
ミラちゅん拍手だね！
Mirachan, applause!
え、ホイップっぽいもの分かった？わし、世界に存在するホイップっぽい形の物これしか知らないのじゃん。
Eh, you figured out something whipped cream-like? I only know one thing in the world shaped like whipped cream.
プリンタ、ブレイクタくだったんだけど、違うのかな。
It was printer... break-ta? Wonder if it's different.
つっちゃんの一択、超可愛いんだけど。
Tsu-chan's one and only choice is super cute.
なんでよ！確かに、なんか人間の内臓とか言い出しそう。
Why! True, it sounds like she'd say human internal organs or something.
こわい、これ怖い！エンマ、ソフィアと言えばみたいな感じじゃの。どういうこと？
Scary, this is scary! Enma, it feels like "speaking of Sophia". What do you mean?
え、でもあの、ソフィア関係ないからね、これ。ソフィアークイズじゃないのじゃん。そうだよ！
Eh, but you know, Sophia has nothing to do with this. This isn't a Sophia quiz. That's right!
イグノーベル書クイズだからね！
It's an Ig Nobel Prize quiz!
あれ、違う？もしかして。
Huh? Is it wrong, perhaps?
今回の趣旨をお分かりでない？
Do you not understand the purpose of this time?
え、ふ、え？でも、とある生き物のから、一部分
Eh, hu, eh? But, a part of a certain creature's body...
大丈夫、ヒントとか大丈夫？みんな
Are you okay, are hints okay? Everyone...
ヒントあるの？
There are hints?
いや、別にもうみんなヒントいらないんだな、もう
No, if everyone doesn't need hints, then already...
いらないのじゃん！
We don't need them!
でも、自信ある！
But we're confident!
お、自信ある！
Oh, you're confident!
何類？
What class?
え、それ言ったらさ、違うの、違ったらさ、はずかしいじゃん。何類？
Eh, if I say that, if it's wrong, it'd be embarrassing. What class?
え、何類かわかってない人がいる。
There are people who don't even know what class it is.
まあね、ノズルですからね。
Well, you know, it's a nozzle.
ノズル、ノズル。あ、ノズルってやつね。ノズルってやつ。
Nozzle, nozzle. Ah, that "nozzle" thing.
の、のから始まる、え、の
Starts with "no", eh, "no"...
いや、大丈夫、自信ある！自信あります！
No, it's fine, we're confident! We have confidence!
お、皆さんじゃあ回答って揃ったかな？
Oh, everyone, have your answers lined up?
じゃあ
Well then.
うん。
Yeah.
お、じゃあ今回はきょうこからちょっと見ていこうかな、ちょっと待ってね。今から、みんなの回答を映すモードに映します。おっ。
Oh, then this time let's start by looking at Kyoko, wait a moment. From now on, I'll switch to the mode displaying everyone's answers. Oh.
お、近づいた。いぇーい！
Oh. We got closer. Yay!
ではでは
Now, then...
じゃあまず狂気の回答お願いします。
First, please give us your mad answers.
ほっ
Ho!
かまきりの手！
Mantis arms!
ほお？
Oh?
それはどういう理由から？
What's the reasoning behind that?
だってやっぱさ、3Dプリンターだから、すごい強くなきゃいけないと思うのね。
Because since it's a 3D printer, I figured it needs to be really strong.
ああ、なるほど。
Ah, I see.
で、かまきりって最強なのね。
And mantises are the strongest, right?
ああ、確か に。
Ah, true.
特に手が。
Especially their arms.
はいはいはいはいはい。
Right, right, right, right.
だからかまきりの手くらいしかないかなって思った。
So I thought it'd probably be something like a mantis arm.
なるほどね。
I see.
いやでもすごいこれはいい考察なのではって感じがしましたけど、果たして正解はどんなんでしょう。
Well, it feels like a really good deduction, but I wonder what the correct answer actually is?
ではでは、
Now then,
続いて、続いていこうかな。
let's move on to the next one.
うん。
Yeah.
じゃあ続いての回答どうぞ！
Now, please show us the next answer!
ほっ！
Ho!
だんごむし？
Pill bug?
え？
Huh?
え、これざまの、待って、部位、部位が、えっと、だんごむしのなにしていうところまで。
Wait, which part of the pill bug—up to what part of it?
体、あ、体体？
Body—oh, body body?
体を、え、だんごむし全部使って、覗きに
Use the whole pill bug body to peer into...
え、掴みやすくない？
Eh, isn't it easy to grab?
掴みやすい？
Easy to grab?
覗きを掴む？
Grab the peeping?
覗く？
Peep?
え、そういうことじゃないの？掴、え、掴むんじゃないの？
Wait, isn't that it? Grab—wait, aren't you grabbing it?
掴む？
Grab?
あの、ホイップクリームの、そう先端部分をだんごむしにするんだ。
Um, you make the tip of the whipped cream a pill bug.
え、みたいな形？え？だん…
Eh, like that shape? Eh? A pil—
え、待ってやばい！やばい、自分で話してて自分で行ってんだ自信なくなってきたのになに！
Wait, oh no! I'm talking and losing confidence in what I'm saying, what the heck!
はあ……
Hah...
え、だってさ、だんごむしってさ、こう
Wait, because pill bugs, like, do this...
ちっちゃいところとさ、ちっちゃくなってて、でかくなってて、ちっちゃくなってるじゃん、体の構造。
They have small parts, then they get bigger, then smaller, right, their body structure.
うん。
Yeah.
はあ。
Hah.
だから、え、良くない？っていう、出しやすくない？
So, wouldn't that be good? Like, wouldn't it be easy to squeeze out?
え、ねぇ、うん、出しやすくない？
Hey, right, um, isn't it easy to squeeze out?
え、何してんの？
Eh, what are you doing?
どこに何を入れてどう出すのじゃ？
Where do you put what and how do you squeeze it out?!
あはははは！
Ahahaha!
え？
Eh?
あの、お尻から繰り出して、そしたらひになっちゃう、お尻になっちゃう！
Um, you squeeze it out from the butt, and then it becomes a butt, it becomes a butt!
お尻からじゃ！
From the butt!
え？違う？
Eh? No?
極肛門ですのじゃ！
That's an extreme anus!
いや、え、形がかわいそうだよ！
No, eh, its shape would feel so pitiful!
形、形、形だけど思い浮かべたらだんごむししか無理。
Shape, shape, shape, but when I think of it, pill bug is the only thing.
お尻からどっから出すの、すずり？
Where do you squeeze it from the butt, Suzuri?
え？
Eh?
お尻から入れてどっから出すの？胃袋？
You put it in the butt and where does it come out? The stomach?
うわあ、ちょっとつーちゃん！非人道的すぎるのじゃ！
Whoa, wait, Tsu-chan! That's way too inhumane!
やばすぎる！
That's way too crazy!
え、待って、本当にやるわけじゃないよね？
Wait, you're not actually gonna do it, right?
いや、やる、やるから研究をだって。
No, I'm doing it—I'm doing research, you know.
ちょっと、某やばいね、すごい映画のことちょっと今一瞬頭によぎりましたけれど。
Wait, a certain terrifying, incredible movie just flashed through my mind for a second.
ああ、ねぇ、怖いんだよ。
Ah, jeez, it's terrifying.
あれ、だんごむし人間ね。
Ah, the Human Centipede.
うん、そう、だんごむし。
Yeah, right, centipede.
はい、じゃあ最後、メラチの回答いきましょうか。
Alright, then let's go to Merachi's final answer.
え、あのさ、あの、私知ってるんじゃが、クイズ番組で一番最後に残される人って正解者。
Um, you know, I happen to know that the person left until the very last on a quiz show is the winner.
確か に！
True!
そうだ！ま、確かにね、正解者が最後に持ってかれる傾向ありですのじゃ。
That's right! Well, indeed, winners tend to be kept for last.
メタ読みのメラだから。
Because Merachi is reading the meta.
のじゃ。
Indeed.
自信ありのじゃ。
I'm confident.
じゃあ行きましょう、メラチの回答はこっち！ほっ！
Let's go then, Merachi's answer is this one! Ho!
はい！サラマンダーのしっぽですのじゃ！
Yes! It's a salamander's tail!
から、メラのしっぽが使われた可能性があるってこと？
Does that mean Merachi's tail might have been used?
いいの？それはメラチ的には。
Is that okay with you, Merachi?
いいよ。
It's fine.
だってやっぱ犠牲ってつき物じゃから。
Because sacrifice always comes with the territory, after all.
科学の研究のために。
For the sake of scientific research.
しっぽ、え、そんな、そんな体張らんできえんよ、別に。
A tail? Eh, you don't have to risk your body like that for it, really.
のじゃ？
Huh?
え、でもさ、あのさ、ホイップクリームの出すところってさ、なんて言うんじゃろ。
Eh, but you know, the part where you squeeze out whipped cream, what do you call it?
あの、三角っぽくて、何、三角水っていうの？あの、入れるところが結構太めで出すところが狭めみたいな感じのがおるじゃろ。
Like, triangular—what is it, a triangular pyramid? The part where you put it in is pretty thick and the part where it comes out is narrow.
感じのがあるじゃろ？
You know what I mean, right?
で、サラマンダーのしっぽちょうどいいと思うのじゃ、絞りやすそう。
And I think a salamander's tail is just right, it looks easy to squeeze.
本当だ！
True!
だしなんかこのなんかヒレ？ヒレみたいなさ、背びれみたいなの付いてるからさ、でも滑らない。
Plus, it has these fins, like a dorsal fin attached, so it won't slip!
すごい！
Amazing!
え、じゃあもううちらで試してみよう、メラチのしっぽでもしかして。
Eh, then let's try it ourselves with Merachi's tail, perhaps?
え、マジで？
Eh, seriously?
お、だって正解のね、今から正解出すだけ、それよりもいい3Dプリンターできるかもしれん。
Oh, since we're just about to reveal the correct answer, we might even make a better 3D printer than that.
え、でもわし入ってこないよ、一、一、残機1。
Eh, but I won't fit, one, one, 1 life left.
え？あ、ちゃう。
Eh? Ah, wait.
切らない方向でできないかな、なんとか。
Can't we do it somehow without cutting it off?
確かに出し口だけとか？
True, just the nozzle opening or something?
えだから口から材料食べて、そしたらしっぽから出るみたいなさ、そういうシステムない？
Eh, so eat ingredients from the mouth, and then it comes out from the tail, like, is there a system like that?
おいおいおい、ちょっとつーちゃんの影受けすぎなのそれ。
Hey hey hey, you're getting too influenced by Tsu-chan there!
ここはヤな話ですのじゃ？
This is getting grim, isn't it?
ってなわけで、じゃあね、もう正解何かわかんないですからね。
That being said, well, we don't know what the correct answer is anymore.
2026年にイグノーベル技術賞を受賞した研究では とある生き物の体の一部を 3Dプリンターのノズルとして 利用しました。 なんの生き物の、どの部分でしょうか?
[Title: In a study that won the 2026 Ig Nobel Prize in Technology, part of a certain creature's body was used as a 3D printer nozzle. What creature and which part was it?]
A. 蚊の口(吻)
A. Mosquito's mouth (proboscis)
うわ、おし！
Whoa, dang!
蚊の口、あの、尖ってる使用する部分ですね。
The mosquito's mouth—um, the sharp part that they use.
えー！すごい！
Wow! Amazing!
確かにな、チュルチュル出せそう。
True, looks like it could squeeze stuff out smoothly.
で、そうそう。できたよね。
Yeah, exactly. They made it.
そちゅるちゅる出す適気なところで、蚊はさ、血をね、吸ったりするじゃん。
And where they suck things up, mosquitoes, you know, suck blood.
それがそれに適してるんじゃないかっていうので、
So researchers thought, wouldn't that be suitable for it?
へえ。そう、研究者の方考えて、あ、これいけるじゃんってなったらしい。
Right. Researchers thought about it and apparently went, "Oh, this could work!"
え、すごっ！え、あんな細いもの扱えるんだ！
Whoa, amazing! You can handle things that thin?!
めっちゃ小さいのね、だって。
It's super small, you know.
こちらがね使ってるような普通の3Dプリンターで言うと、かなり高解像度の3Dプリンターのノズルに利用されたんだけど
Compared to the regular 3D printers we use, it was used for the nozzle of a much higher-resolution 3D printer,
ま、このね、3Dプリンターこういう感じであるところを、これをこれで置き換えるっていう
and replacing parts of this 3D printer setup like this...
ええ！すごーい！
Whoa! Amazing!
え、天才すぎるんだけど発想が。
That's genius! What an idea.
そう、でそれを実際やってちゃうってのがまたすごいよね。え、すごいな。
And actually doing that is amazing in itself, right?
高解像度3Dプリンターのノズルの一部として死んだ蚊の口を利用したらしいです。
And as the tip part of that high-resolution 3D printer, they used a dead mosquito's mouthparts, apparently.
え、もし蚊をパチンってやったら、連れてったらいい？そこ。
If you go "pachin" like that, can you take it there?
上手いことに殺せなくて潰しちゃったらさ、使えないよ。
If you crush it without killing it, you can't use it, right?
そこじゃなくて、折れちゃったりする時にね、ちゃんとそういううまいことやったと思うんですけど。
So at that moment, they must have done something clever, I think.
でねこの、じゃあ蚊の口ね、別に普通のノズルでもええやんって思うんですけど、これね実は蚊の口を使ったノズル、実際ちゃんと使えて、
And you know, this mosquito mouthparts nozzle can actually be used,
でなんと、市販の高性能な金属チップのその解像度を上回るような結果も得られるらしい。
and it even outperformed the resolution of commercially available metal chips.
え、すごっ！
Whoa, amazing!
ええ。
Yeah.
やっぱね、蚊の口ってその、やっぱ小さいためにさ、そのほぼ真っすぐで固くて細い管になってるから、やっぱこれがね、ノズルの先端に使うのにちょうどよかったらしい。
Mosquito mouthparts are so small, straight, hard, and thin, so it turned out to be just right for a nozzle tip.
え、ちょうどいい！
That's amazing!
いや発想がやばいわ。
The idea is wild!
ほんとに痺れるよね。
Yeah, it really gives you chills, right?
すごーい！
Amazing!
こういったね、生き物と機械を組み合わせるような滅釣りガ…！え、待って、すごい！これはびっくりしてる今。
Wait, combining living creatures and machinery... I'm so surprised right now!
嬉しい！
I'm so glad!
やっと正解できたかな、これでやっと。
I managed to get it right, right? Finally!
え、違うよだって3Dプリンター再現するみたいな書いてあったからさ、ギリギリ団子虫ならいけるかなって。
Wait, it said 3D printers are being reproduced, so I thought maybe I could barely manage "dango-mushi" (pill bug)?
あ、そうゲットしたのか、なるほどね。
Oh, so you guessed that? I see.
最近、3Dプリンターで作るものの質問だと思ってた。
Wait, I thought the question was about what you make with a 3D printer!
ノズルの説明もしたいよね。
You should explain about the nozzle, too!
はい、ええということでこういったね、生き物と機械を組み合わせるような分野をバイオハイブリッド工学って言うんですが、
So fields combining living creatures and machinery are called biohybrid engineering,
この2023年のイグノーベル賞も実力バイオハイブリッド工学の研究が与えられてて、例えばね、その雲の死体をマジックハンドとして利用した研究とかもあったりします。
and the 2023 Ig Nobel Prize was also awarded for biohybrid engineering research, like using dead spiders as mechanical hands.
え、すご！
Huh, amazing!
雲ってさ、8本足あるじゃん。あれをマジックハンドとして利用したらしい。
Spiders have eight legs, right? They used those as mechanical hands!
どうやって？
How did they do that?
そう、それもね、またね、筋肉の能力とか？
That also involves... like, muscle power?
技術、技術！
Technology, technology!
技術で、技術で！
With technology!
すごいよ。そんな、あの、あれじゃないよ、ファンタジーの世界じゃないよ、イグノーベル賞は。
It's amazing! It's not like fantasy or anything, the Ig Nobel Prize.
い、すごいのだ！
That's amazing!
はい、ていうね、まず第1問、はい、蚊の口で3Dプリンターを作ってみたでしたー！
So, that was our first question: trying to make a 3D printer using mosquito mouthparts!
超惜しかったじゃん私。
You got it right, didn't you?
そう、だから今日はかなりいい線いってたんです。
Yeah, so today you had a pretty good thread going.
なになにって。だんごむし惜しくない？おいたちも結構惜しいよ。
What do you mean? "Dango-mushi" (pill bug) is not that close, but "tsuzuri" (writing) was quite close!
え、惜しかったよ、初めに。
Wait, "tsuzuri" was closer, right? Originally.
でもつづりと虫どっちが惜しいかつったら虫じゃない？だってつづりはさ、口書いてないもん。
Well, if you compare "tsuzuri" and "dango-mushi" for which is closer, "tsuzuri" isn't even close because "tsuzuri" doesn't have a mouthpart!
いやいやいや、私ちゃんと全体を表現したから。
No, no, no, I represented the whole thing!
え、サイズ考えたらでも結構近いよ。
Well, if you think about the size, it's pretty close!
まあ、じゃあ次、第2問いきましょうか！
Okay, let's move on to the second question!
はい、じゃあ続いて、第2問いきましょう！
So, moving on to the second question!
ででーん！はい、続いて2026年イグノーベル生体力学賞からの出題です。えー、この生体力学賞はある行動〇〇の定義を考案した功績に対して与えられました。〇〇に入る、とある行動とは何でしょう？
Here we go: "The 2026 Ig Nobel Biomechanics Prize was awarded for research considering the definition of ___. What kind of behavior does '___' stand for?"
わかる？
Do you know?
わかんない
I don't know.
ま、なんかその身体とかの関する話かな？
Well, is it about the body or something?
その、身体の……その、我々の身体的な
Like, the body's... like, our bodily...
身体の力？とか、そうそうそう、身体の研究みたいな感じで捉えてもらえたらいいかなと
Body strength? Yeah, if you view it as research on bodily strength,
まんで……ま、我らが、まあ、することもあるかもしれない、行動ですね
And... well, actions that we might also do sometimes.
するかもしれない、行動？
Actions we might do?
え、VTuberが配信中にしますか？
Eh, do VTubers do that during streams?
あー、それは、しないんじゃないか、いや、わかんない
Ah, I don't think they do... well, I don't know.
そういう、あ、じゃあ、くしゃみとあくびじゃないな
Like... ah, then it's not sneezing or yawning.
ま、中にはそういう人もいるかも、え、何とは違う？
Well, some people might... wait, what's it different from?
お腹鳴るのも違うか
Is stomach growling different too?
あ、違うね、それは違うね。やるからね
Ah, no, that's different. People do that.
え、でも近い？お腹鳴るのに近い？
Eh, but is it close? Close to stomach growling?
いや、どうかな？
Nah, I wonder?
今回のあれはね、実はね、1人じゃあんまできないことかな？
The thing this time is actually something you can't really do alone.
1人じゃあんまできない？
You can't really do it alone?
え、ドキドキしてきた
Eh, I'm getting nervous.
え、な、1人じゃできないこと？
Eh, wh-, something you can't do alone?
一人？では、この定義には当てはまらないかな？
Alone? Then it doesn't fit this definition?
はい、もうここまでいったら
Okay, once it gets to this point,
わかった！
I got it!
お、二人でやるやつ！
Oh, something you do with two people!
二人でやるやつ！
Something you do with two people!
二人でやる事？
Something you do with two people?
確かに二人か
True, two people huh.
一人じゃできないこと
Something you can't do alone.
二人？二人？二人かな？
Two? Two? Two people?
で、定義だって。〇〇の定義
And it's a definition. The definition of XX.
これだ！二人を言わなきゃいけないことでしょう
This is it! It must be something involving two people.
定義を、さだめなきゃ、わからないことでしょう
You have to define it, or you wouldn't know.
ま、まあ、それはね、研究の一環としてね、とある行動の定義をしたんですけどれど
Well, they defined a certain action as part of their research, but
うん
Yeah.
気持ち、平らべてしまった
It got completely flattened out.
え、ちょっと待ってほしんの
Eh, wait a second, Hoshino.
全然思いつかない
I can't think of anything at all.
生体力学
Biomechanics.
二人で生体力学
Biomechanics with two people.
あ、これわかったよ
Ah, I figured it out.
お！
Oh!
これは結構自信ある
I'm pretty confident about this.
自信あり！
Confident!
え、じゃあもうちょいシンキングタイムいい？あ、いいよ、じゃあもう一歩ヒント行きましょうか
Eh, can I have more thinking time? Sure, then let's get another hint.
あ、ありがと
Ah, thanks.
上半身にある……上半身と言うか
It's in the upper body... or rather, upper body.
上半身のどこかの体のパーツを使う行動です
It's an action using some part of the upper body.
え、じゃもう絶対使ったじゃん
Eh, then we definitely just used it.
全身使っちゃった
I used my whole body.
全身使ってるわ
I'm using my whole body.
全身運動しちゃった
I did a full-body workout.
ええと、上半身だけ
Umm, only upper body.
上半身だけ！
Only upper body!
うわ、めっちゃ気持ちいいこれ
Woah, this feels so good.
え、ちょっと、今回ガチで狙いに行きますの、じゃあ
Eh, wait, we're going for a serious win this time, then.
おお！
Ooh!
ソフィア、私とメラチはしそう、それ
Sofia, me and Merachi would probably do that.
え、え、え、え、ちょっと、そんな、そんな！
Eh, wait, no way, no way!
なになに？
What is it?
え、ちょ、違う？何？その反応
Eh, wait, wrong? What's with that reaction?
メラチとキョウコがこ、こ、これを、わあー！
Merachi and Kyouko doing this, waaah!
なにその反応、何なのじゃ？
What's that reaction, what is it?
え、ちょ、違うのかな？
Eh, wait, is it wrong?
え、待って、出てきちゃった
Eh, wait, it just came out.
え、二人が？
Eh, the two of you?
え、ワシとキョウコがしなそうなこと？
Eh, something me and Kyouko wouldn't do?
いや、わかんない、別にして、別にいいんだけどさ、でも別にこれはソフィアが言うあれではないから別にね
Well, I don't know, it's fine either way, but it's not really something Sofia would say so...
え、じゃあ、考え直すのじゃ
Eh, then I'll rethink it.
これ、これ、私もうファイナルアンサーで
This, this, I'm already at final answer.
え、じゃあちょっと、なんかのやつ？ちょっと、なんかのこと、でしょ？
Eh, then some kind of thing? A bit of some kind of thing, right?
なんか、なんかソフィアの反応的に結構、あの、なんだろう、生々しいさ
Like, judging by Sofia's reaction, it's pretty, um, raw.
やっぱ関係性がなかなか出来上がってる人じゃないとできないこととかでしょ？
After all, it's something you can only do with an established relationship, right?
はあ？
Huh?
じゃあこれ、分かったのじゃ！と言えば
Then if I say, I figured it out!
それで上半身でしょ？
And it's the upper body, right?
一択なのじゃ！
It's the only choice!
一択だ！
Only choice!
これしかない
This is the only one.
え、一択ですのじゃ？ ですのじゃ？
Eh, is it the only choice?
これで一致したかな？
Did we agree on this?
行けたか、みんな？
Did you make it, everyone?
大丈夫？
You okay?
行ってきます
I'm going.
じゃあみんなの回答を見ていこうと思うので
Well then, let's look at everyone's answers.
じゃあ、誰からにしようかな
Well, who should we start with?
今回はメラチからいこうかな
This time let's start from Merachi.
おお！
Ooh!
のじゃ！
Noja!
はい、じゃあメラチの回答は、こちら！
Yes, then Merachi's answer is here!
ズバリ、糸電話ですのじゃ！
Boom, it's a string telephone!
ロマンチック！
Romantic!
糸電話なんて結構仲いい人としかしないんじゃない？
A string telephone is something you only do with close friends, right?
確かに
True.
ちょっとなんか
A bit like
ASMRなんじゃない？
Isn't it ASMR?
雑談か
Chit-chat.
なるほどね。結構、結構ソフィアがああいう反応するのも頷けますのじゃ
I see. I can understand why Sofia reacted like that.
なるほど
I see.
ああ、確かに。なるほど、いや、確かに、確かに
Ah, true. I see, no, true, true
かも知んない
Could be.
じゃあとりあえず つづりいこっかな？
Well then, shall we start with the spelling?
うん。
Yeah.
じゃあねえ、えーと…待て、つづりの回答がこちら！
Well then, um... wait, here is the spelling answer!
よしよしでしょう
It's gotta be 'There, there'.
え、なんで二語合わないの？
Eh, why don't the two words match?
うん？
Hm?
よしよしって下半身でしないの？
Don't you do 'there, there' with your lower body?
え？ ちょ…、え、手とか…、あ、下半身よしよし
Eh? Wait... E, hands... ah, lower body 'there, there'.
ちょっと待って、め、めら…しないの？よしよし
Wait a minute, Me, Mera... you don't? 'There, there'.
めら、しないのじゃ？下半身 スリープしましたのじゃ？
Mera, you don't? Did your lower body go to sleep?
ちょっと待って、ちょっと、一旦ね、一旦ね。
Wait a second, hold on, just a moment.
おちつこっか。ステージ、ステージ…
Let's calm down. Stage, stage...
あ、そ、そうそう、ワンチャンさあね、なんか違うのかなって思ったんだけど…
Ah, right, right, maybe, you know, I thought it might be something different...
だってきょおことめらがワンチャンそれかもしれないんでしょ？
Because Kyouko and Mera, there's a chance it could be that, right?
で、こと、つづりはいつもしてるからさ、違うじゃん？
And Koto, you always do spelling, so it's different, right?
ってことは、ワンチャン二人でなんかよしよしお互いし合ってる定期的なものがあってもいいんじゃないかなと思って、よしよしにした。
So I thought, hey, maybe there's some regular thing where the two of you pet each other, so I went with 'there, there'.
なるほど。あー。
I see. Ahh.
よしよしぐらい普通にするよね、うちら。
We normally do 'there, there', right us?
いやそうそう。つづりよりしてること書かれてたってもって感じなのじゃん？
Yeah, exactly. Like, even if it says something we do more than spelling, right?
いやもうしてるけどなっていう。
Like, 'Well, we already do that'.
そんなん、そんなんじゃない？
Isn't it like that?
結構自信あったんだけどな、これについては。
I was pretty confident about this one, though.
え、でもなんかしたことないことじゃよ。
Eh, but it's something we've never done, you know.
え、でもなんかその考え自体は確かにってなった。
Eh, but I felt like 'true' about the thought itself.
え、でじゃ？
Eh, really?
よし、じゃあ最後京子の回答いきますかね？
Alright, shall we go with Kyouko's answer last?
はい！はい、じゃあ京子の回答はこちら！
Yes! Yes, well then Kyouko's answer is right here!
チュー♡
Kiss♡
チュー。
Kiss.
え、めら違う！めら違う！お見え付いちゃったよちょっと！
Eh, Mera, no way! Mera, no way! You guessed it, didn't you, a bit!
そ、そんな配信で言うことじゃないのじゃ。
Th-That's not something you say on a stream.
え、これは京子はなんでチューにしたんですか？
Eh, why did Kyouko make it a kiss?
えだって、だって、上半身使って二人ですることで、もししたら私とめらがもうする、するかもしれないことって言ったら、あとちゅうぐらい…
Well because, because, doing something together using our upper bodies, if you talk about something me and Mera might do, maybe a kiss...
配信でいうことじゃないですのじゃ。残ってないかな？チュー以外のことはもう全部やったなって思って、じゃああとチューかって思います。はい。
That's not something you say on a stream! I thought, 'Is there anything left?' We've done everything except kissing, so I thought, 'Well, maybe a kiss next.' Yes.
でもお前のまだしてないのじゃ。嘘だった。
Wait, you haven't done it yet! That was a lie.
確かに、まず糸電話かな段階的にはね。
True, step-by-step it'd be string telephones first, right?
でもなんか糸電話に関しては、それは生態力学じゃなくて、もしかしたら物理なんじゃないかなって思いまして。
But regarding string telephones, I thought maybe that's not biomechanics, but physics.
確かに！それは一緒！だからチューなって。
True! That's the same! That's why it's a kiss.
なるほどね。じゃあちょっとそろそろ回答に移りましょうか？
I see. Well then, shall we move on to the answer soon?
はい。じゃあ今回の第二問の回答いきましょう。
Yes. Well then, let's go to the answer for the second question this time.
正解はこちら！
The correct answer is here!
えー！？チュー！接吻！
What?! Kiss!
ということで、おー、京子正解！イエーイ！やったー！
So, oh, Kyouko is correct! Yay! Yay!
愛の勝利だわ！愛の勝利！イエーイ！
Victory of love! Victory of love! Yay!
合ってたんだ！合ってた！
It was right! It was right!
合ってるの！？のじゃあ？
It was right?! Really?
正解はチューだよ。
The correct answer is kiss.
え、ちなみに何なん？あ、いい質問ですね。
Eh, by the way, what is it? Ah, good question.
じゃあちょっとキス（接吻）の定義を皆さんには今からお教えしましょう。
Well then, let's teach everyone the definition of a kiss (seppun) from now on.
キスの定義: 攻撃的ではない相互作用で指向性があり同種間で口と口により行われる唇や口腔をある程度動かすが食物の受け渡しは伴わない接触。
Definition of a kiss: Non-aggressive interaction with directionality, performed between members of the same species mouth-to-mouth...
指向性があリってのはどういう意味なのだ？
What does 'directionality' mean?
その誰としようみたいな。
Like, who are you doing it with.
あ、意識を持って、誰にでもいいわけじゃなくて、そうそう、わけじゃなくて
Ah, with intent, not just with anyone, exactly, not just anyone...
えじゃあ猫とじゃダメなんだ、同種間だから。
Eh, so with a cat no good, because it's same-species.
そうだね、今回…、あ、サラマンダーじゃ違う。
That's right, this time... ah, salamander is different.
サラマンダー同士なら…、あ、そっか！え、私と…、え、ちょ、京子とメラッチはチュー一生できんねんのだ？
Between salamanders... ah, I see! Eh, me and... eh, wait, Kyouko and Meracchi can never kiss?
キスの定義においてはちょっとキスチューではないかなって感じかな？
In terms of the definition of a kiss, maybe it's not quite a kiss/chu?
その人が定めた定義だからさ、別にもっと別の定義があってもいいんですよ、全然ね。
It's a definition set by that person, so there's totally room for other definitions, you know.
うちたちの定義作る？
Shall we make our own definition?
え、こういうとき人間はあの、これはチューじゃないからみたいな感じで二次創作をするって聞いたことある。
Eh, I've heard that humans in times like this make fanfiction like 'this isn't a kiss, so...'.
ということは、え、京子、めらのあ、そんな…
That means, eh, Kyouko, Mera's... ah, like that...
ちょっとね、そろそろね、まだね、あの、口ですからね、
"Well, you know, it's about time, since it's still, you know, mouths..."
まだちょっと、深夜にはまだ早いんでね、あんなところにちょっとしてこうかっていうところで、
it's still a bit early for late-night stuff, so we thought we'd put it somewhere like that,
ま、ちょっと、なんでね、このキスの定義をしたかっていうちょっと話をね、させていただければと思うんですけど、
Well, why did we define a kiss? We'd like to talk a bit about that,
なんてね、こんなね、わざわざ、こんな大変な定義をしたのか。
Why on earth did we go through the trouble of making such a difficult definition?
はい、こちらですね。霊長類におけるキス行動を比較検討するため、はい、このキスの定義ってのを研究者さんが考えられたっていうことらしいです。
Right, here it is. In order to compare and examine kissing behavior in primates... apparently, researchers came up with this definition of a kiss.
比較検討ってどういうことなの、じゃあ?
What does 'compare and examine' mean, then?
その、例えば人間同士のキスってのがあって、でも霊長類のね、例えばチンパンジー同士もキスとかするんですよ。
For example, there are kisses between humans, but primates, like chimpanzees, also kiss each other.
それをちゃんと研究の土俵に乗せるには、そもそもキスって何なのかっていうのを、その人間のキスだけじゃなくて霊長類とか他の動物にもちゃんと適用できるような定義を付けないと、その研究の土俵には乗せないよねっていうので、
In order to properly put that on the table for research, we need a definition of what a kiss is in the first place, applicable not just to human kisses, but to primates and other animals as well, otherwise we can't bring it to the research table,
あえてこういうね、こういう定義をちゃんと
so they purposely made this kind of definition.
確かに。
True.
口授しで、そのご飯与える動物とかもいるから、
There are animals that feed food mouth-to-mouth, so...
そうそうそうそう、それと差別化するためってことなのかな。
Right, right, right. Is it to differentiate from that?
そういうこと、今回は研究ではキスとはしませんっていう感じで、ちゃんとその人間
That's why kisses like that won't be considered kisses in this study—so that kisses done by humans,
がやっているように、そのちゃんと思考性があって、コミュニケーション的な感じでやってるようなキスを
with intent and communicative nature, can also be properly
ちゃんと動物にもね、考えられるようにってところで定義されたっていうことらしいです。
considered for animals, or so it seems.
えー、すごいじゃん、深えじゃん、チューの定義。
Whoa, that's amazing, so deep, the definition of a kiss.
そう、そうだよ。深いんだよ。で、これちゃんとね、定義した上で研究、さっきの比較検討したことで、
Right, exactly. It's deep. And by properly defining this and conducting the comparative study mentioned earlier,
その、やっぱキーストっていうのは、その現存する大型類人猿のほとんどで見られて、
kisses are seen in almost all extant great apes,
で、さらに、その原生人類の禁煙にあたるネアンデルタール人って、みんな聞いたことあるかな?
and furthermore, Neanderthals, who are closely related to modern humans—has everyone heard of them?
あ、聞いたことある。
Ah, I've heard of them.
で、このネアンデルタール人でもさっきのキスの定義で言うこの
And this comparative study showed that it's highly likely kisses, as defined earlier,
キスが行われていた可能性が高いっていうことも、この比較検討で分かったっていう。えー!
were also performed by Neanderthals. Whoa!
じゃ、結構昔から、そうなんですよ、キスって。
So it's been around for a long time—that's right, kissing.
歴史深えんだ。
How profound in history.
そうなの。
Indeed.
なんでするのじゃ、そもそも。敵意がないことを示すため?
Why do they do it in the first place? To show no hostility?
あとこれもね、いろんな意図があったり、そうあの、これね、論文、ももとの論文があるんだけど、
And there are various intents behind it too—there's an original research paper about this,
その、それこそプラトニックなキスとか、プラトニックじゃないキスとか、
like platonic kisses and non-platonic kisses,
なんかそういうことがちゃんと、そんなのがあるのじゃ?
things like that are properly... such things exist?
論文にちゃんとプラトニック、プラトニックじゃないみたいなことも、
it's summarized in tables in the English paper,
ちゃんと表にまとめられてたりしたりするので、
so for those interested,
そのあの英語の論文なんですけど、ご関心ある方はすげえ面白いので、あの概要欄に載せてます、文献情報。
it's super fascinating, we've put the reference info in the description box.
あるんだ。
It's there.
ございます。ありがとうございます。
Thank you very much.
はーい、てなわけでね、これからみんなチューしよ、じゃなくて、ちゃんと正確に、
Right, so from now on, instead of just saying 'let's kiss,' let's accurately say
えー、攻撃的ではない相互作用で指向性があり、口と口で行われ、唇や口腔をある程度動かし、食物の受け渡しは伴わない接触を接触しようというようにしましょうね。
'non-hostile, directional interaction, performed mouth-to-mouth, moving lips/oral cavity to some degree without food transfer, let's have contact' like that!
はーい。
Okay!
じゃあ、また人間について詳しくなったのじゃ。
Well, we've learned more details about humans.
はーい、ぜひぜひ皆さんちゃんとしたね、定義でね、はい、使ってみてください。
Yes, please do use it with the proper definition!
ということで、第2問、はい、ノーベル生理学医学賞からの問題でした!
With that, question 2 was a question from the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine!
のじゃー! 面白ーい!
Noja! So interesting!
はい、ということで、今回は京子か正解ということで1ぽりーとですね。
Right, so this time Kyoko got it right, so 1 point lead.
やったぜ!
Yay!
おー、確かに!
Oh, true!
え、当てられちゃった! じゃ、ちょっと研究を追おうぜ。近づきましたけれど、じゃあ
Eh, you guessed it! Well then, let's pursue the research. We're getting closer, so
続いて第3問に行こうと思います。
next let's move on to the 3rd question.
のじゃー! はい。
Noja! Yes.
じゃ、続いて、第3問はよいしょよいしょ。こちら。
Now then, the 3rd question is... here it is.
はい、えー、2026年イグノーベル化学賞を受賞した研究で、とある生き物の「ミルク」の結晶は、同じ質量の牛乳の3倍のエネルギーを含んでいることが明らかになりました。
Right, um, in a study that won the 2026 Ig Nobel Chemistry Prize, it was revealed that the crystal of a certain creature's 'milk' contains three times the energy of cow's milk of the same mass.
その生き物とは何でしょう?
What is that creature?
結晶? ミルクの結晶なんだ。
Crystal? Milk crystal.
え、ヒント? ヒントヒントヒント。
Eh, hint? Hint hint hint.
ネタバレしたのじゃ。
You gave a spoiler.
これね、ソフィアもね、この研究知るまで、え、この生き物ミルク出すの?って
Right, Sophia also didn't know until this research—'Eh, this creature gives milk?'...
え? ああ、なるほど。
Ah, I see.
えっ、じゃあ違うのじゃ。
Eh, so that's wrong.
ヤギだと思ったのじゃろ。
You thought it was a goat, right?
ヤギのミルクではないですね。
It's not goat's milk.
のじゃー!
Noja!
なんか、イグノーベル賞ってね、すごい引っかかるんだよね。
Ig Nobel Prizes are really catchy, you know.
はい、はい、はい。そう。
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right.
排泄、排泄で同じ質量。
Excreting, same mass through excretion.
だから、たぶんエネルギー効率がめちゃくちゃいい
So, probably the energy efficiency is insanely good...
動物だと思うんだよ。
I think it's an animal like that.
エネルギー効率がいいてどういうこと？
What does it mean for energy efficiency to be good?
ちょっとした栄養素でめちゃくちゃ動けるみたいな、そういう生き物だと思って、便秘がいい？
Meaning it's a creature that can move a lot with a tiny bit of nutrients... constipation is good?
ああ、なるほど。いいですね。
Ah, I see. That's nice.
となるとこれかな。
Then maybe this is it.
あ、ちょっと待って。
Ah, wait a second.
みんなの回答、秘密のせいで。よし、あぶねえ。
Because of everyone's answers, keep it secret. Phew, that was close.
便秘がいい生き物のミルクの結晶。
Milk crystals of a creature with good constipation.
便秘がいいってことは、あんまご飯食べないでいっぱい動けってことやから、少食そうな
Good constipation means you can move around a lot without eating much food, so an animal that looks like a light eater...
生き物がいいんじゃない？
...would be good, right?
わかったのじゃ。便秘マックス。
I figured it out. Constipation Max.
もう一個ぐらいヒントいる？大丈夫？
Do you need one more hint? Are you okay?
え、くれるの？
Eh, you'll give me one?
え、あるの？
Eh, there is one?
行きましょうか。え。
Let's go. Eh.
これね、イグノーベル賞ですからね。
This, you know, is an Ig Nobel Prize, after all.
イグノーベル賞を受賞するような研究ですからね。
It's research that wins an Ig Nobel Prize.
なにその前置き？
What's with that preamble?
そう、イグノーベル賞を受賞するような生き物ってね、何でしょうね。
Right, what kind of creature wins an Ig Nobel Prize, huh?
あ、じゃあこっちか。
Ah, then this one?
あ、じゃあ、あ、じゃあこっちだ。こっちだ。分かった。
Ah, then, ah, then it's this one. This one. I get it.
あの、それではかったわ、私も。
Ah, I got it too, then.
絶対これ。
Definitely this.
これ100の自信、ちなみに。
100% confident, by the way.
そのイグノーベル賞を受賞するようなみたいな目覚めの一言共通認識がないのじゃ。
There's no common consensus like 'waking up to win an Ig Nobel Prize' or anything.
イグノーベル賞あるあるがあるじゃん。
There are common Ig Nobel tropes, right?
まあね、その、なんかさ、普通の生き物だったら、まあまあなるけど、えっ、ここれ？となるような。
Well, you know, for ordinary creatures, it's like 'meh', but 'Eh? This?' kind of thing.
ああ、目覚め得意ですね、じゃあ任せてくださいのじゃ。
Ah, you're good at waking up? Then leave it to me!
え、じゃあ違うのか？
Eh, so it's different?
こういうことじゃの？分かったのじゃ。
Is that what it means? I figured it out!
目覚め。
Waking up.
え、わかんない。なんでみんな僕コロロ？え、何？
Eh, I don't get it. Why is everyone 'Cororo'? Eh, what?
え、でもこれじゃないかな。目覚め使いのメラですのじゃ。
Eh, but isn't it this? It's Mela, user of awakening.
任せてほしいのじゃ。
I want you to leave it to me.
なんだろう？すずりじゃの？
What could it be? Suzuri?
いや、逆の逆行くのじゃ。
No, going the opposite way.
これぐらいしか浮かばない。
This is about all I can think of.
じゃあ、皆さん回答出揃いましたか？大丈夫か？のじゃ。
So, everyone finished answering? Are you ready? Right?
はい。
Yes.
はーい。じゃあ、ちょっとみんなの回答を見ていきたいと思います立てに。よいしょ。よいしょ。
Okay! Well, let's take a look at everyone's answers vertically. Heave-ho. Heave-ho.
よし、いきます。ほ。
Alright, here we go. Ho.
じゃあ、今回はどうしようかな。
So, what should we do this time?
すずりから行こうかな。
Let's start from Suzuri.
お。お。
Oh. Oh.
じゃあ、まずすずりの回答はこちら。
Well, first, Suzuri's answer is this.
コマラ。
Koala.
え、これじゃない？だって、便秘がいいんでしょ？
Eh, isn't it this? Because, good constipation, right?
で、ミルクでそうでしょう？
And milk, so right?
引っ付いてたら便秘悪いのじゃないの？あんま動かないって。
If they're clinging, isn't constipation bad? Since they don't move much.
ってことはさ、普段さ、コアラってさ、引っ付いてるイメージあるからさ、いっぱいなんか、あれじゃない、清々してそうじゃん？どう？
That means, normally, koalas have this image of clinging to things, so they seem refreshed with a lot of... right? How about it?
そうね。うん、あんま動けないのかな、もしかしたら。
True. Yeah, maybe they can't move much.
あれ？便秘が、あれ？あれ、動いてないからいっぱい元気があるんじゃないの？
Huh? Constipation is, huh? Huh, since they're not moving, don't they have a lot of energy?
そうもとれるな。
You could take it that way.
うん。よし。確かに。うん。そうもとれる。
Yeah. Alright. True. Yeah. You could take it that way.
え、でも、ちゃんとすずり、その自分の考えを持って、ちゃんとそれを伝えられてるのは、すごい、すごい、素晴らしいことだよ。
Eh, but Suzuri, having your own thoughts and properly communicating them is amazing, amazing, wonderful.
はい。ありがとうございます。噛むって答えたんです。
Yes. Thank you very much. I answered 'koala'.
いやでも、すごい。いや、全然コアラありうる回答だと思うし。
No, but amazing. No, I think koala is totally a possible answer.
まだ回答全然わかんないからね、正解ね。
We still don't know the answer at all yet, the correct one.
うん。はい、ありがとうございます。
Yeah. Yes, thank you very much.
はい、じゃあ続いて、メラちいこっかな、じゃあ続いて。
Alright, then next, Mela, let's go, then next.
のじゃあ。
Right.
メラちの回答は、こちら！
Mela's answer is here!
人間なのじゃ！
It's humans!
え？
Eh?
人間のミルク？母乳ってこと？のじゃ。
Human milk? You mean breast milk? Right?
おお、その心は、えっと、最初、えっと、最初、ラクダにしたのじゃ。
Oh, the reasoning is, um, at first, um, at first, I made it a camel.
便秘よさそうと思って。
Thinking it might be good for constipation.
で、その次、さらに目覚めして、なんか違う生き物にしたのじゃ。で、それがの逆が人間なのじゃ。逆、逆張りの逆張りが人間。
And then next, waking up even more, I changed it to a different creature. And the opposite of that is human. The opposite of a contrarian's contrarian is human.
逆張りの逆張りが人間なのじゃ。だって、だってさ、イグノーベル賞でさ、
The opposite of a contrarian's contrarian is human. Because, because, you know, in the Ig Nobel Prize,
人間のミルクがさ、なんか、あの、牛乳よりさ、すごくあったらさ、おおってならん？
if human milk, you know, somehow, um, was way more than cow milk, wouldn't you go 'Whoa'?
確かに。
True.
人間だったらさ、おおってならん？
If it's humans, wouldn't you go 'Whoa'?
確かになる。
That's true.
確かに私たち普段牛乳飲んでるけど、それよりもっていう驚きがあるよね。
True, we usually drink cow milk, but there's the surprise that it's even more than that.
ああ、確かに。
Ah, true.
そうそう。身近な
Right, right. Close by...
これはいいたよみ
That's a good read, yomi.
のじゃして正解はどうなんだ
So, what is the correct answer?
では最後強行行きましょう 京都この回答はこちら
Then let's finally go with... Kyoto's answer is here!
ゴキブリ
Cockroach?!
えっってミルク出んの？
Eh? Do they produce milk?
っていうところ 私知らないの、出るかどうか
That's the thing, I don't know if they produce milk or not.
でもソフィアが「え、こいつミルク出るんだ」って驚いてたってことは、多分なんか鳥類とか哺乳類とかそっち系じゃないの。
But since Sophia was surprised like, "Wait, this thing produces milk?", it's probably not birds or mammals or anything like that.
多分超意外な類い
Probably a super unexpected kind.
で、ここでムジマで絞って、で、ゴキブリっていうのは、なんかね、油いってけど5日間動けるくらいすごいんよ。
So narrowing it down with Mujima... and cockroaches can move for like 5 days even without oil, it's amazing.
あ、確かに
Ah, true.
エネルギー効率の神だから、あとイグノーベル賞っぽい生き物ナンバーワンだから
Because they're the gods of energy efficiency, and also the #1 creature suited for the Ig Nobel Prize.
ね、ふーん、確かに
Right? Huh, true.
ナンバーワンなのだいつは、イグノーベル賞といえばなのも
It's number one, when you say Ig Nobel Prize, that's it.
だから、ありって書いてあったんだけど最初は、も、ゴキブリしかないでしょと思って
So, I wrote "ant" at first, but then I thought, it has to be a cockroach.
おお、ヒントからそこまでたどり着く
Oh, reaching that far from the hints!
はい、ゴキブリです
Yes, it's a cockroach.
なじもゴキブリだと思った
Naji also thought it was a cockroach.
ゴキブリの逆に人間にした
I reversed cockroach to human.
見てた、見てた。えなち途中ゴキブリだったのに人間に変えたのソフィア見てたよ。
I was watching, I was watching! Sophia saw you change it from cockroach to human halfway, Enachi.
のじゃあ、果たしてゴキブリなのか、人間なのか、はたまたコアラなのか！
So, is it really a cockroach, a human, or perhaps a koala?!
はい、じゃあ正解を見ていきましょう！
Well then, let's look at the correct answer!
こら、こい、こら、こい、こら、こい。人間こい、人間こい、こら、こい。
Come on, come on! Human come on, human come on!
正解はこちら！
The correct answer is here!
ゴキブリ正解！
Cockroach is correct!
みぽみぽみぽみぽ、きょうこすごいじゃん！
Mipo mipo, Kyoko, that's amazing!
まじかよ！
Seriously?!
あ、つづり、ごき、ぶ、り、昆虫苦手
Ah, spelling: c-o-c-k-r-o-a-c-h. I hate insects.
ゴキブリだけはどうしても
Cockroaches are just impossible no matter what.
え、待って、や、ソフィアのこのイラストもだめ？
Wait, is Sophia's illustration bad too?
あ、え、それゴキブリなの？
Ah, wait, is that a cockroach?
笑った
I laughed.
ゴキブリなのこれどっからどう見ても
Is this a cockroach no matter how you look at it?
え、ご、ご、ごき、ゴキブリ？顔の位置すごくないだって
W-wait, c-c-c-cockroach? Isn't the face position crazy?
顔？
The face?
顔は確かにここにはないけど、本物のゴキブリより可愛いしょ、ぽに、ぽに可愛いなった方がね、見やすくしてくれてるじゃん。
The face isn't really there, but it's cuter than a real cockroach, right? It makes it easier to look at.
のじゃ、ねえ
Right, right?
ご、ゴキブリ顔も置いといて可愛いから見れるわ。
Leaving the cockroach face aside, it's cute so I can look at it.
あ、よかった。うん、ゴキブリだけどねっていうことで
Ah, good. Yeah, it's a cockroach though, so...
はい、きょうこ2問連続正解すごい！すごいのだ！
Yes, Kyoko getting 2 questions right in a row is amazing! Amazing!
これは当てる、そんなに当てる気なかったからでも、え、マジで？
I wasn't really planning on guessing this right, but seriously?!
いや、もうがっつり正解でしたということで、いや、そもそもさ、ゴキブリってさ、卵で生まれるイメージありませんか？皆さん。
Well, it was totally the correct answer. Wait, isn't everyone under the impression that cockroaches hatch from eggs?
ある、ある、ある。そう、カプセルにつくっていう。
There are, there are! Right, they form a capsule.
ねえ。ただ今回のね、その対象となっているゴキブリちゃんっていうのは、その胎生ゴキブリの話なんですよ。
Right. But the cockroach in question this time is actually the viviparous cockroach.
その胎生ってのが、人間もね、あの、お母さんのおなかの中で赤ちゃん育てられて、それ出産って感じなんだけど
Viviparous means, just like humans, babies are raised inside the mother's belly and then born.
このゴキブリちゃんも同じように、お母さんのおなかの中で育って、そっから出てくるみたいな、そういうね、生まれ方をする
This cockroach too, grows inside the mother's belly and comes out from there, that kind of birth process.
ゴキブリちゃん。そういう種類のmいる？
Cockroach-chan. Are there types like that?
そう、それがね、このディプロプテラプンクタータじゃん。
Yes, that's this, Diploptera punctata.
え、名前可愛い。
Eh, the name is cute.
名前だけ見たらさ、ちょっとおしゃれな料理屋さんの料理の名前なのだじゃん。
Just looking at the name, it sounds like a dish from a stylish restaurant.
コースとかに混ざってても、え、そうそうおかしくない。
Even if it's mixed in a course, it wouldn't be weird at all.
前菜だよね、絶対ね。ね、前菜にいても気づけないのだじゃん。
It's definitely an appetizer. Right, even if it's an appetizer, you wouldn't notice.
そこのね、ディプロプテラプンクタータちゃんはなんと、母親の体の中でミルクを飲んで育つ胎生ゴキブリちゃんでね、名前もあれ、かっこいいんけれども
Diploptera punctata is a viviparous cockroach that grows by drinking milk inside the mother's body, and while the name is cool...
そう、こんなに面白い性質を持っているゴキブリちゃんでということで
Yes, it's a cockroach with such interesting characteristics.
ここね、ゴキブリちゃんのそのミルクなんだけど
Now, about that cockroach's milk...
これね、栄養豊富なこのミルク結晶っていうのをね、赤ちゃんの中で結晶化して
They crystallize this nutrient-rich milk crystal inside the babies...
で、この結晶が、同じ質量の牛乳の3倍以上のエネルギーを持つらしいです。
And apparently, this crystal holds more than 3 times the energy of the same mass of cow's milk.
で、じゃあ、母体からボニューを飲んで、そのボニューを飲んだ先の子供の腹の中からミルク出したの？ボニューを、え、待って、えっと、子供、赤ちゃんの腹の中の結晶を取り出して試したってことなのじゃ？
So, did they drink milk from the mother, and then extract milk from the belly of the child who drank that milk? Wait, did they extract the crystals from inside the belly of the baby and test them?
的な感じが、ちょっと研究のその具体的なちょっとプロセスまで終えてないんだけど、一応この実際ミルク自体は、その赤ちゃんが摂取してそれで結晶化するようなプロセスを辿るらしくて。
Something like that—I haven't quite finished looking at the specific process of the research, but apparently, the actual milk is ingested by the baby and goes through a process where it crystallizes.
で、なんて結晶化するといいのかってこれはまだね、ちょっと研究で、あの確定かどうかはちょっと言えなかっていうふうに書いてあったんだけれど
And as for why it's good to crystallize it, it was written that researchers couldn't say for sure yet whether it's confirmed.
でも、やっぱりその、結晶化することで、その、なんていうか、ランチパックみたいな感じでさ、必要な時にその栄養素をさ、制御された形でその放出でき るっていうので
But still, by crystallizing it, like a lunch pack, you can release the nutrients in a controlled manner when needed.
好きな時はその栄養を取り出せるみたいな、そういうために結晶化してるんじゃないかみたいな
It's probably crystallized so that you can extract the nutrients whenever you like, something like that.
赤ちゃんが任意のタイミングで食事を取れるってこと？みたいな
Like, does it mean the baby can take meals at any arbitrary timing?
必要なときに、その、結晶化することで、栄養を取り出せる
When needed, by crystallizing it, they can extract nutrients.
じゃなーいみたいな。これはねちょっと論文でも
Or something like that. This, you know, even in papers
プロバブリ的なくらで書かれてた、あの、お、おそらく的な感じで書かれてたから
it was written in a sort of probable... probably kind of way, so
そう、あの、確実かどうかってちょっとね、ソピア的にもわかんないんだけれど
Right, so whether it's certain or not, Sophier doesn't really know either, but
ま、そういう人目で、その、栄養豊富なミルクを結晶化してるんじゃないかっていう
well, it's said that perhaps they crystallize that nutrient-rich milk,
はい、ことが言われてまして。
yes, things like that have been said.
えーすご。
Wow, amazing.
ゴキブリ。
A cockroach.
ねー。だから日本にもさ
Right? So even in Japan...
いや、これはね海外、基本海外のプンクタータちゃんだった気がする。
No, I think this was overseas, basically overseas, Punctata-chan.
プンクタータちゃん？
Punctata-chan?
プンクタータちゃん。
Punctata-chan.
なんか、かわいく見えてきちゃったの、どうしよう？
Somehow she started looking cute, what should I do?
え、可愛いよね。ゴキブリってさ、結局自分の家の中にいなければね。
Eh, cute right? Cockroaches, well, as long as they aren't inside your own house,
ね。めっっちゃ可愛い。
right? Super cute.
え、綴りも書いてみる？プンクタータちゃん。
Eh, want to try spelling it too, Punctata-chan?
あ、会話はしないけど
Ah, we won't converse, but
会話はしないけど、なんか、あの、展覧会、あの、なんて言うんだ、シークレットインショーみたいなのあったら、ぜひ見に行けるかも。
we won't converse, but if there's like an exhibition, like a secret insect show, maybe we can go see it.
え、じゃん！
Eh, right?
プンクタータちゃん、いつかプンクタータちゃん見に行くか。
Punctata-chan, maybe go see Punctata-chan sometime.
え、行きたい！
Eh, I want to go!
え、ちょっと待りこま？
Eh, wait, Marikoma?
4人組みが行ったら
If a group of four goes,
あまり不快感しないで、いただきたいのじゃ。
we'd like you not to feel too uncomfortable.
のじゃ。
-noja.
これがアイツか！
So this is the one!
のじゃ、今日この声がでかいから終わったのじゃ。
-noja, Kyoko's voice was so loud it's over now -noja.
ものすごい端から端まで聞こえる声で
With a voice that echoes from edge to edge,
これがあのミルクのゴキブリか！
So this is that milk cockroach!
え、でもうれしい。中身っちゃ、敬意持って貰えて、すごくうれしい、ありがとう！
Eh, but I'm glad. Getting respect for the contents inside, I'm super happy, thank you!
解説が全部面白い。
All the explanations are funny.
え、面白い！のじゃ！
Eh, funny! -noja!
あ、やったー！
Ah, yay!
うれしい、ありがとう、ありがとう！
I'm happy, thank you, thank you!
じゃあ、最後、第4問、行こうかなと思います。
Well then, for the last question, Question 4, I think we'll go with it.
はい。なんですけれど？
Yes. But what is it?
はい、今、点数をみると、え、今日こ2点、ミラッチ綴り詩が0点なんですよね。
Yes, looking at the scores right now, Kyoko has 2 points, and Miratch and Tsuzuri have 0 points.
のちあー
Nochiaa
じゃ、最後の問題だけ
Well, for the final question only,
なんか、最後の問題だけ、1兆点とか？
like, for the final question only, one trillion points or something?
いや、もう10兆くれていいよ。いいでしょ？
No, you can give us 10 trillion. That's fine, right?
5000兆点ほしいのじゃ！
We want 5,000 trillion points -noja!
ほしい！
We want it!
じゃあ、最後の問題だけ、5000兆点にしましょう！
Then for the final question, let's make it 5,000 trillion points!
おー、やったー！
Oh, yay!
やったるぞ！
We're gonna do it!
じゃ、なんでね、絶対当てる絶対当てる。
Well then, definitely hit it, definitely hit it.
第4問を制したものが、い、ちょうど、これを制するということで、皆さん気合いを入れてお願いします！
The one who conquers Question 4... to conquer this, everyone put your spirit into it, please!
行くぜ！勝つのか！
Let's go! Will we win?
絶対当てる！
Definitely hit it!
川の経験いただくのじゃ！いただくぜ！
Receiving the experience of Kawa! We'll take it!
はい、じゃあ、行きましょう。最後、第4問は、こちら！
Alright then, let's go. Finally, Question 4 is this!
2026年イグノーベル土壌科学賞は、
The 2026 Ig Nobel Prize in Soil Science was
1000枚の〇〇を埋め、2ヶ月後に掘り出した功績に対して与えられました。
awarded for burying 1,000 sheets of [blank] and digging them up 2 months later.
この、〇〇に入るものとは何でしょう？
What is the thing that goes into [blank]?
シンキングタイム、スタート！
Thinking time, start!
6つ。
Six.
え、だから2ヶ月後に掘り出せたらすごいものでしょう？靴はなくなっちゃう
Eh, so if you can dig them up 2 months later, it must be something amazing, right? Shoes would disappear
靴がなくなっちゃう。確かに。
Shoes would disappear. True.
あ、なくなっちゃう系か。じゃあなんか、タイムカプセルとかじゃ
Ah, disappearing type? Then like, time capsules or something
でもないじゃん、タイムカプセル。
but wait, not time capsules.
あ、わかった。埋めて、マイって、お金とかでしか聞いたない。マイと言えば
Ah, I got it. Burying, mai (sheets/bills), I've only heard of it with money etc. Speaking of mai,
いいところにね、いい着眼点ですね、それは。
Good point, good perspective, that is.
マいといえば、じゃろうな。
Speaking of mai, probably.
マいといえば。
Speaking of mai.
えーー、そうだな、2ヶ月も普通は残ってないんでしょ？
Eeeh, I see, normally they wouldn't remain after 2 months, right?
そして皆さん、皆さん。
And everyone, everyone.
そろそろあれですよ。
It's about time.
これ、イグノーベル賞ですからね。
This is the Ig Nobel Prize, you know.
あ、確かに。
Ah, true.
あ、わかった！
Ah, I got it!
わかった！わかった！
I got it! I got it!
わかんない。
I don't know.
イグノーベル賞といえば、メタ読みだこれ！
Speaking of the Ig Nobel Prize, this is meta-reading!
え、マジ？それ知らないよ今日子なんで知っているの？
Eh, seriously? I don't know that, Kyoko, why do you know?
えでも、ミラッチとか綴りもさ、これまでの傾向でさ、ちょっとイグノーベル賞って
Eh, but, Miratch and Tsuzuri too, based on previous trends...
なんかこういうとこついてくるようなみたいな、ちょっと分かってきたんじゃない？
haven't you figured out that it tends to hit on these kinds of things?
これ、まいでしょ？
This is mai (sheets), right?
えー？
Eeeh?
まいでしょ？
Mai, right?
でも、これ埋まってたら嬉しいけどなー。
But, it would make me happy if this was buried.
嬉しい。
Happy.
なんだろう。
I wonder what.
えじゃあもう、大ヒントいっちゃおうかな！
Eh then, shall I give a big hint!
え、大ヒント？
Eh, a big hint?
なになになに？
What what what?
えー、研究の背景を聞かないと、これをやってる人がいたら、え？何これ、高度な変態さん？って思うじゃん。
Uh, if you don't hear the research background, if someone is doing this, you'd think, "Eh? What is this, an advanced pervert?"
変態さん？
A pervert?
変態？変態さん？
Pervert? Advanced pervert?
わかった。
I get it.
変態さんって何考えてるのじゃ？
What are you thinking, calling them a pervert?
わかんない変態さんだから。
I don't know, because they're a pervert.
え、それ、あの、書いて見てて大丈夫？これ。
Eh, is it okay to write and look at this?
あー、や、一応、ギリギリ、ギリギリ大丈夫じゃないかなとソピアは思っている。
Ah, well, for now, Sophier thinks it's just barely okay.
え、これ？
Eh, this?
ありえないの。え、違うのかな？
Wait, isn't it...
え、不安になってきた。
Ugh, I'm getting nervous.
え、1000枚の…
Uh, 1000 sheets of...
え、でも、消えちゃいそうなものじゃろ？
Well, isn't it something that disappears?
なんじゃろ？
What could it be?
せんべい？
Senbei?
でもさ、掘り出したってことはさ、消えないものなんじゃないの？
But if you dug it up, wouldn't it not disappear?
うん。
Yeah.
でも、化石って言ってるよ。
Oh, but they said it's a fossil.
確かに。
True.
え？それ違うのかな？
Eh? Is that different?
それが綺麗に出てくる土壌を作ったことがすごいよってことでしょう、きっと。
That means making a soil layer that looks clean is amazing, right? Kiita.
1000枚の何かを…
1000 sheets of something...
うーん、え、なんだろう。
Ugh, what could it be?
いいですね、土壌科学賞ですからね、これはね。
Well, it's the IgNobel Prize for soil science, you know.
うん。
Right.
いい土壌を作ったねってことだよね？
It means making a good soil layer, right?
1000枚埋めでれるものでしょ？
1000 sheets of something buried, right?
うん。
Yeah.
え、これは…
Eh, this is...
これか？
Is this it?
こんにゃくするわ。え、変態さんなんじゃろ？
Konnyaku? Wait, is it a freak?
うん。
Yeah.
ちょっと、ちょっとアイドルとしてどうかなとは思いつつ…
I'm thinking maybe it's an idol, while wondering...
まあ、これもこれもね、クイズイグノーベル賞のために…
Well, this is also for the Quiz IgNobel Prize...
体張ってくれるのか？
putting your body on the line?
やっぱ
Well,
本気で、あの、カバーの経験狙いに行ってまさんじゃ。
they're seriously aiming for a cover photo shoot, aren't they?
さすがだねらっち。
As expected of Neratchi.
任せてくださいな、じゃ。
Leave it to me, then.
え、ねえ大丈夫？これで、じゃ。
Eh, are you okay? With this...
うん、最後、ファイナルアンサー？
Alright, last, final answer?
はい！
Yes!
じゃあ行きましょう、正解を。
Then let's go! The correct answer...
え、発表する前にみんなの回答を見ていきましょう。
Uh, before announcing, let's look at everyone's answers.
ちょっと待ってね。えっと、よし、大丈夫かな。
Hold on, let's see...
あぶね、一気にめくるとこだった。
Ah, careful, I almost flipped it over suddenly.
おいし、じゃあ見ていきましょう。
Oish! Then let's take a look.
ほ、どうじゃ？
Ho! What about you?
うん。
Yeah.
いや、どうしようかな。これはじゃあ、最初は京子からいこっかな。
Well, what should I do? For this, I'll start with Kyoko, I guess.
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ京子の回答は、こちら！
So, Kyoko's answer is this!
トイレットペーパー！
Toilet paper!
ええ？トイレットペーパー。
Eh? Toilet paper?
ね、めちゃイグノーベルでしょ、トイペ。
Right? That's totally an IgNobel Prize.
確かに。
True.
確かにイグノーベル…
True, IgNobel...
でも1000枚で紙。
1000 sheets is paper.
そう。トイレットペーパーって紙？
So, is toilet paper paper?
あの、切れ目のところでちょうど、この切って…
Um, at the cut-off point, right?
ロールじゃない？
A roll, right?
切って前にした。だから、事前で私はブリーフかなって思ってます。
Before cutting it, right? So, beforehand, I thought it was a brief, you know.
はい。
I see.
ブリーフってなんじゃ？
What's a brief?
ブリーフってなに？
あ、えっと、じゃあ解説は求めないで、もう…
Ah, well, I won't ask for the explanation, just...
あとで、あとでコメントで教えてもらう。いや、言って大丈夫なんだけど。
You can tell me later in the comments. Just tell me later.
なんかその辺りがイグノーベルっぽいかなって私は思った。
It's just that the atmosphere felt kind of IgNobel-like, I thought.
なるほどね。確かに。うん。
I see, true.
なるほどね。じゃあ続いて、綴り行こうかな？
I see. Then let's move on and spell it out, shall we?
うん。
Yeah.
はい、じゃあ、ずっぶりの回答は、こちら！
Alright, then, Tsuppuri's answer is... this!
あ、間違えた！あ！あ！
Oh, wait! Oh!
あー、なんかチラッと見えた気が。あれ？
Oh, I accidentally showed it, wait.
あ、あ、あ、ごめんごめん、あの間違えちゃった。
Wait, wait, wait, I made a mistake.
あ、あの、誰も見てない。みんな忘れるビーム！
Hey, no one was looking, everyone forget this beam!
はい、まず、まずね、ずっぶりの回答からいきましょうかね。
Alright, first, first, let's start with Tsuppuri's answer, shall we?
え、そう、くつしただったらさ、
Eh, right, socks.
丸めてさ、入れればさ、ワンチャン2ヶ月後に取り出してもそのままポンって出てきそうじゃない？
if you roll it up and put it in, then even if you take it out two months later, it would come right out flying, wouldn't it?
はい、はい、はい、はい、はい、はい。
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
え、確かに。くつした埋めてたらだいぶ恐ろしいのよ。
Eh, true. If you buried socks, that would be pretty terrifying.
いや、怖いよね。
Scary, right?
え、そっか。2000枚っていけそうじゃない？くつしただったら2000枚。
Wait, 2,000 sheets sounds doable, right? For socks, 2,000 sheets?
え、くつしたの単位って2000枚？
Is 2,000 sheets the unit for socks?
1000枚、1000枚ね。うん。
1,000 sheets, 1,000 sheets, right? Yeah.
あ、1000枚が1000枚。え、でもいけそうじゃない？これ結構自信あるよ。
Ah, 1,000 sheets is 1,000 sheets. But it seems doable, right? This actually has confidence, yo.
うん、全然いけると思う。
Yeah, I think it's totally doable.
うん、自信ありです。
Yeah, I'm feeling confident.
いや、これまでの綴りを見てすごい、あの、ソピアの成長を感じてすごく嬉しいよ。
Man, looking at Tsuppuri's spelling so far, I feel like I can feel her growth and I'm really happy.
バカにされてるのじゃ。
You're making fun of me, aren't you?
え、バカにされてるのね、さすがに。
You're making fun of me, right? Seriously.
いや、よかった。このね、クイズを通じてまた綴りがね、すごい、いや、嬉しいなって思ってる。
Well, I'm glad that this quiz has also made Tsuppuri's spelling so great. I'm happy.
バカにされてる、ソピアに！
You're making fun of Sopia!
やった！
Hooray!
はい。
Yes.
じゃあ、最後、え、おみは何でかぶってしまった？あ、眼鏡外した。
Alright, then, lastly, why did Omi put on glasses? Ah, she took them off.
あれ？外した？
Wait, did she?
のじゃ、何だったのじゃ？
Noya, what was it, noya?
じゃ、おちいめらさんの回答をいきましょう。こちら！
Let's check out Ochimera-san's answer. Here it is.
はい、本気で推測しましたのじゃ。
Yes, I seriously deduced this, ja!
春画ですのじゃ！
Shunga, desu, no, ja!
あー！
Ah!
春画って何？
Shunga? What's that?
あ、ソピア先生に聞くのじゃ。
Ah, let's ask Sopia-sensei.
ソピア先生、春画ってなんですか？
Sopia-sensei, what is Shunga?
ちょっと、違うの、悪いところだけソピアに解説させて。
Hold on, I'll only explain the bad parts to Sopia.
え、なんですか？
What is it?
あの、
Well, it's...
いにしえの、いにしえの、
Inishie no... Inishie no...
あ、これジェネキョ？
Ah, is this Genekyo?
あ、ジェネキョか、それは。
Ah, Genekyo, right?
ジェネキョか。そういうことか。ジェネキョか。
Genekyo! Ah, so that's it, Genekyo.
うちら江戸知らないからさ。
We don't know about the Edo period, so...
うん、確かに。いにしえの…
True, inishie no...
ねえねえ。
Let's see.
脳みそみたいな。
Something like brain...
(笑)
(Laughs)
ちょっと分かった？
Did you figure it out?
(笑)
(Laughs)
うーん、もじゃ？
Hmm, maybe.
もじゃ？
Maybe?
やっぱ、これ和紙じゃからさ、
Well, washi is Japanese paper, so...
けっこう、けっこう残りづらいんじゃないかなって思って。
It might be a bit hard to last long, I thought.
うん、まあ、確か。
Yeah, true.
でも昔から存在しているものって、現在のね紙とかよりも耐久度が落ちるなと思っていて。
Things from a long time ago have lower durability than current paper, I think.
おぉ。
Ah.
だから結構なんか、何ヶ月後からに無くなっちゃう気がしていて。
So I thought it might disappear a few months later.
おぉ。
I see.
あ、これ和紙ってあれね、あのジャパニーズペーパーの和紙。
Oh, "washi" as in Japanese paper, right?
あ、123じゃないほうね。
Ah, not 1, 2, 3!
あ、そうそうそうそうそう。和紙ね和紙ね。
Oh, right, right, right, right, Japanese paper.
そう、わか、若が。
Yeah, waka, waka.
だから、まあ、で、あのノーベル賞っぽいそのなんだろな、あの、結構触れづらいところに触れていく感じみたいなのを合わせてこちらになりましたのじゃ。
So, like, something Nobel Prize-like, something that touches on somewhat obscure areas, we got this.
なるほど、なんかすごい回答ふざけてんのかって思ったけど、すごい考察を聴くと確かにって。
I see, so you thought it was a joke answer?
ね、いいかもって思うよね。うん、もじゃ。
Yeah, sounds plausible, right?
うん、もじゃ。
Yeah.
いやあ、果たしてね、ね、トイレットペーパーなのか、靴下なのか、はたまた春画なのか！
So, is it toilet paper, socks, or could it be shunga?
(笑)
(Laughs)
はあ、じゃあそろそろね、回答の方していきたいと思いますのは、そい、よいしょ。
Well, let's finally reveal the answer!
いまが、現代で春画を埋めてるやつ。
filling in shunga these days?
いや、いたらだいぶ、だいぶ怖いじゃろ。
If so, that's pretty, pretty scary.
それじゃから。
That's...
だからこそ。確かに、それは高度な変態さんだが、さすがに、うん。
That's why, that's why! That is indeed an advanced mutant, though, as expected. Mm.
確かに。
True.
はい、じゃあいきましょう最後、第4問の正解は、こちら！
Right, let's go. The correct answer for question 4 is... this!
あー！
Aah!
もじゃー！
Moja!
パンツ！
Underwear!
ブリーフじゃ！
Briefs!
(笑)
(Laughs)
え、そっちゃん、え、しかもブリーフじゃん、それ。
Wait, briefs?
パンツでしたー！
It was underwear!
はーい、や、けっこうね、惜しかったね、みんなね。
Man, everyone was so close!
え？わかってきてたよね、イグノーベル賞よね。
Right? You were getting close, Ig Nobel style.
うん、わかってきてた。
Yeah, we were getting closer.
しかも、けっこう、つづり狙いそうだった。
And plus, we were almost able to spell it out.
ねえ。
Right?
いや、つづりも本当に惜しかった。
Seriously, the spelling was really close too.
え、途中までさ、変態さんって言われてて、下着って書いたんだよ。
Wait, halfway through, I heard "mutant" and thought I should write "panties," so I wrote that.
わあ、惜しい！
Oh! So close!
下着って書いたんだけど。
I wrote panties, but...
下着1000枚ちょっと大変かと思って、
Writing "panties" for 1,000 items might be a bit tough, I thought.
靴下だったらさ、ほら2個あるじゃん、だからいけるかと思って、靴下にしたんだよね。
If it's socks, there are two, right? So I thought, maybe I can go with socks!
準備のことまで考えてくれてたんだね。
So you thought it through to the preparation stage!
そう、そうそう。惜しいことしたあ！
Yeah, so close!
はい、じゃあね、そのパンツを1000枚埋めたらしいんですけど、や、わかります？みなさんが言いたいこと。
Right, so they buried 1,000 pairs of underwear, but... do you guys get why?
なんでパンツ埋めたん？
Why did they bury underwear?
確かに。
True.
何がきっかけよ、それ。
What was the trigger for that?
「なんで埋めたんや」ってもいますみなさん。
"Why did we bury underwear?" everyone's asking.
ね。
Right?
曲が差してしまった。
It crossed their wires.
インスピレーションが欲しかった。
They wanted inspiration.
一番準備しやすかったとか？
They wanted to be the most prepared, or something?
ああ。
Ah.
なんでパンツそんなあるん？
Why would they have underwear?
だって、もういらないパンツとか集めたらさ、いっぱい集まりそうじゃん。
If you collected that many unnecessary pairs of underwear, you wouldn't even have that many!
確かに、でもそんなにいっぱいは並なんない。
Even so, you wouldn't have that many lined up.
はい、じゃあもうこれはね、正解いきましょう。
Alright, let's go with the correct answer for this one.
正解は、土壌の健康状態を調べるためですね。
The correct answer is: To check the health condition of the soil!
どういうこと？
What does that mean?
パンツで？
Underwear?
そう、パンツで。
Yeah, underwear.
どういうこと？
What?
そう、これね、今回の取り組みっていうのが、その対象となった研究の取り組みがその市民科学って言われるものなんですけれど、
So, this, well, this initiative was part of what became known as citizen science.
これ市民科学、シティズンサイエンスとかも言われたりするようなものなんですけれど、
This is also called Citizen Science, or Citizen Science.
これが、その研究者じゃない一般的な、あの、一般市民の方にその実際の研究に参加してもらって、それによって研究者だけでは取れないデータを取ったりとか、その科学への関心を高めてもらったりするような試みのこと、市民科学って言うんですけれど、
And what this is, is getting regular citizens who aren't researchers to participate, and through that, gathering data that researchers alone couldn't get, and increasing interest in science—that's the kind of attempt called citizen science.
もともとね、この市民科学、土壌科学における市民科学の例として
Originally, in citizen science and soil science, as an example of citizen science,
ティーバッグ指数というものがありました。
there is something called the tea bag index.
へえー！
Whoa!
そう、これはね、土の中に紅茶のティーバッグを埋めて、で、その土の中でその有機物とかがどういうふうに分解されるのかっていうのを調べるための指標だったんですけれど、
So this was meant to check how organic matter decomposes in the soil by burying a tea bag in the dirt.
そう、これがね、測定にやっぱ手間がかかっちゃったりとか、
Yeah, but doing this requires a lot of effort for measurements,
あと、これがね、市民科学って言ったりね、やっぱたくさんのね、人に協力してもらいたい
and also, since it's called citizen science, they want a lot of people to cooperate.
ものなんで、やっぱりやっぱティーバッグを埋めるからみんな集まれって言ってもさ、あんまり人がそこまでね、集まんなくったり、する中で研究者さんね、考えました。
So even if you say "everyone come bury tea bags," not that many people show up, and in the meantime, the researchers thought...
「いや、どうすればたくさんの人に協力してもらえるだろう？」
"How can we get lots of people to cooperate?"
あ、なんかユーチューバー的なやっぱ人集めにみんな必死なんじゃないの？
Ah, since we're like YouTubers, everyone goes all out to gather people, right?
そう、そうなんだ。
Right, exactly.
だから、研究者さんたち検討を重ねて、
So, the researchers consulted each other and...
そうだ！！パンツを埋めてもらおう！！ってね。
"That's it! Let's have them bury underwear!"
え、なんでパンツになるの、それで？
Wait, why underwear after all?
え、埋めたくない？研究の一環で自分のニアにパンツみんな埋めたくない？
Well, don't you want to bury underwear as part of research? Like, wouldn't it look good on you?
埋めたい。
I want to.
パンツだったら埋めたいよね。
Right, if it's pants, we'd wanna bury them, right?
土壌に飢えてるって聞くのじゃ。
I hear it starves the soil.
そう、やっぱシュールなね、そう、笑い的なの好きでしょ？そういうね。
Right, it's surreal, you know? Everyone likes that kind of comedic angle, right?
俺何やってんだろ感がね。
That "what am I even doing?" feeling.
うん、みんなに、やっぱり速効力があるんちゃうかっていうことで、
Yeah, thinking "doesn't this have instant effectiveness for everyone?",
で、実際にパンツ埋め、埋める人あつまれって言ったらなんと
and when they put out a call saying "gather people to bury pants!",
1000人の市民が集まったらしい。
apparently 1,000 citizens gathered.
おお、埋めるぜって。
Whoa, let's bury 'em!
そのまち気が狂ってる。
That town is out of its mind.
違った、そんな狂っちゃダメでしょ！研究にって、もうみんな疲れてますのじゃ。
Wait no, you can't be that crazy! For research, everyone's exhausted.
研究にちゃんと協力しようって、全員で、全員でね、その参加してもらうってどういうこと言うんだ、あっちめら！
Saying "let's properly cooperate with research", everyone, you're asking them to participate... what are you saying, you guys!
もじゃあ、でもさ、これさっきツズリが考えてたの合ってってこと、ツズリこれ正解でもいいんじゃない？ダメなのは？
Moja, but wait, what Tsuzuri was thinking earlier was correct, so couldn't Tsuzuri's be the correct answer?
ねえ、答えにニューログしてなきゃ意味ないし。
Right, if you don't log the answer it's meaningless.
そう、だね。それ言ったら、京子もね、あのブリーフっていうところね、ちょっと売っててだから、言ってだから。
Right. That being said, Kyoko also sold briefs over there, so she said.
ででもね、めっちゃね、ツズリね、いい、マジでいい線行ってて、実はね、このパンツに至るまでに、研究者さんあの靴下を埋めてもらうことも考えてたらしい。
And you know, Tsuzuri was on a really good track. Actually, before pants, they considered socks.
えっ？
Eh?
あっ？
Oh?
えー？
Eeeh?!
だって、パンツに、
Because, in pants...
で、やっぱ靴下とパンツならパンツだろつって。
Well, between socks and pants, it's gotta be pants!
これが、
That's why...
なるほどね。
I see.
はい、で、最終的には2000枚以上のパンツも埋めたらしいです。
Right, and apparently in the end, over 2,000 pairs of pants were buried.
ええーっ！
Eeeh?!
すごっ！すごいのだじゃ！
Amazing! That's amazing!
すごいパンツでんだいアート。
That's some amazing pants... modern art.
確かに。んでちょっとね、これ実際パンツ埋められたらどうなるか皆さん気になりませんか？
True. And wouldn't you all be curious what happens when pants are actually buried?
気になるー！
We're curious!
さあ、こちらがね、はい、見てもらいましょう。
Now, let's have you take a look at this.
はいのTバッグ指数ならぬパンツ指数っていうので、
Right, the "pants index", rather than T-back index,
そう、これがその土壌によって、なんて、分解めっちゃされるような土壌だったので、その、今ね、京子が、あの、よけてくれた、その、めっちゃもうパンツのね、あと形もねみたいな感じになるんだけど、
So, depending on the soil, if it's soil where things decompose a lot, like the one Kyoko just saved for us, it becomes like, the shape of the pants is mostly gone...
分解能力はそこまでの土壌とかだったら左のような感じで、パンツのね、面影が残ってるみたいな。
If it's soil with lesser decomposition ability, it looks like the one on the left, where the traces of the pants remain.
えっ、これ同じだけ埋めてもこれだけ差が出るんだ？
Eh, even if you bury the same amount, there's this much difference?
あっ、期間はね、一緒にして、なんで土壌によって、やっぱりね、その分解能力ってのが変わるから、それによってそのなんて、その土地の土壌がどういう状態なのかってのがね、このパンツ指数から分かるみたいな、そういうね、取り組みだったんですと、いうことで。
Ah, the period is the same, so why the decomposition ability changes depending on the soil—based on that, you can tell what kind of state the soil of that land is in from this pants index, that kind of initiative it was.
どっちが土壌が強いのじゃ？なくなるやつと、なくならない土壌どっちが野菜育つ？
Which soil is stronger? The one where they disappear or the one where they don't, which one grows vegetables better?
あっ、野菜とかで言ったらやっぱり分解能力が多分高い方がいいんだけれど、そう、右側の方がいいんだけど、ただね、その、じゃあ、いい土壌って、
Ah, when it comes to vegetables, higher decomposition ability is probably better, right, the right side is better, but you know, good soil...
その、やっぱ用途によっても違うから、そうやっぱ、その、畑耕すとかそういうのだったら分解能力高い方がいいけど、そうじゃない普通の森林とかだったら別に分解能力高すぎると逆に、なんか栄養とかがいっぱいになっちゃって、逆に困っちゃうみたいなこともしたりするから、けっこう、いい土壌ってのはけっこう用途によるらしいです。
differs depending on the use. For fields, high decomposition is good, but for normal forests, too high decomposition causes excess nutrients and trouble, so good soil depends on the purpose.
へえ、じゃあ私たちもちょっと今すぐ調べよう、うちの土壌。
Eh, then let's check right now too, our soil.
ねえ、みんなパンツ、埋めて、そのうちの庭はどうかなっての、そう確かめてみてください。
Right, everyone bury pants, and check how your garden's soil is.
埋める！今すぐ埋める！
Bury 'em! Bury 'em right now!
はい、ちなみにこのね、市民科学プロジェクトって、あの日本でもね、あの、このパンツじゃないんだけれど、取り組みとかがなされていて、例えばあのNHKさんとかがそのシチズンラボっていうね、あの、取り組みがされていて、なんかそのみんなの周りにいる蝉どんなの？とか、そういうのをみんなからいろんな情報集めてそれを研究に生かしてこうみたいな、そういう取り組みが日本でもあんのね、もし、ねえ、こういう市民科学興味ある、興味持たれた方はぜひちょっとね調べてみてください。
Right, by the way, this citizen science project, in Japan too, well, not these pants, but initiatives like NHK's "Citizen Lab" gather info from everyone like cicadas to use for research, so if you're interested, check it out.
え、やりたいそれ！
Eh, I wanna do that!
ねえ、面白そう。
Yeah, sounds interesting.
参加したい？
You wanna participate?
やりたい！あ、そういう回りたいで？
I wanna do it! Ah, you wanna join like that?
やるか！どこ埋める？
Let's do it! Where are we burying?
え、今度さ、やってるとき呼んでソピア。
Eh, next time you're doing it, call me, Sophia.
え、呼んでんで！やりたい！
Eh, call me! I wanna do it!
え、うれしい！なんかさ、遊びたいの、みんなめっちゃさ、ソピアのいろんなこと言ってるのに興味持ってやろうって言ってくれるの、マジで嬉しい本当によかったね。
Eh, I'm so happy! You guys talk about all sorts of things about Sophia, and saying you're interested and want to do it makes me so genuinely happy, I'm really glad.
普通におもしろいのだじゃ！
It's genuinely interesting!
話全部おもしろい！
All the stories are interesting!
ええ、うれしい！おっかえったー！
Eeeh, I'm happy! Welcome back!
はい、っていうことで、第4問も終了ということで、
Alright, with that, Question 4 is also finished,
はい、それでは、みなさん、おまちかねの、結果発表に、移りましょうか。
Alright then everyone, shall we move on to the long-awaited results announcement?
おっ！来るか！？
Oh! Is it coming?!
来るぞ！
Here it comes!
皆さん、どうかな、ご自身のほどっていうところで、おいしおいし、ちょっとね今集計中なんだけどね、
Alright, everyone, how is it? Let's check our own soil right now since we're currently tallying up the results...
ちなみにどうでした？改めましてイグノーベル賞クイズ
By the way, how was it? Once again, the Ig Nobel Prize quiz.
面白かったのじゃ！面白かったよマジで
It was so interesting! It was genuinely interesting!
そう言っていただけると、えーすごい
Hearing you say that... is amazing.
あのやっぱずっとクイズ大会やりたくてさ
I've always wanted to do a quiz tournament,
それで結構なので、みんなに楽しんでもらえるかなっていうので
so I really wanted everyone to enjoy it,
準備頑張っててから、そう言ってもらえるとすごく嬉しいよ
and I worked hard to prepare, so hearing that makes me so happy!
超楽しい！
Super fun!
24時間耐久でやりたいこれ。ね？知らなかったこといっぱいじゃったし
I want to do a 24-hour endurance stream of this. Right? There was so much I didn't know,
ああ！
Ah!
なんか、なんだろう、言葉のイメージより難しくない？
somehow, isn't it harder than the image of the words?
ああ！えーそう言ってもらえると嬉しい
Ah! Hearing you say that makes me happy.
ね？面白い でしょ？研究ってさ、そういう真面目な方もすごいね、わあこんなことやってすげえってのもあるし
Right? Isn't it interesting? Research has those really serious sides that make you go "Wow, they did that, that's amazing,"
実際研究者の方ってこういうおもしろいこともいっぱいね、やられてたりもするので
and actually, researchers do a lot of funny things like this too,
うん、ぜひみんな改めてそういうサイエンスとか、ね、研究とかに興味を持ってもらえると嬉しいなって思います
so I'd be so happy if everyone could take a renewed interest in science and research!
みんなも持ったよね、絶対ね、今回で。
Everyone had that too, definitely, with this time.
ああ！
Ah!
持った！
I had it!
めっちゃ面白かった！
It was super interesting!
ソースもね、割と なんか馴染みのあるのキトソピアが選んでくれたのもあるじゃろし
Also, the sources had a sense of familiarity because Chitosopia chose them, right?
あるじゃろしい
Right?
面白かったね！
It was interesting!
ね、めっちょ面白かった！
Right? Super interesting!
面白かった！
It was fun!
さあ、ありがとう、ありがとう！
Thank you so much, thank you!
いやこれで新社長になれるだなんて、ありがたいことです
Man, to become the new president with this, I'm so grateful.
株式50％ありがとうございますのじゃ！リアルだなあ
Thank you for 50% of the stocks, I'd say! So realistic...
じゃあ、そろそろ行きますか
Well, shall we get going soon?
おい！
Hey!
では、今回のクイズイグノーベル賞の優勝者を発表したいと思いまーす！のいちゃ！
Now, we would like to announce the winner of this quiz, the Ig Nobel Prize! Noicha!
優勝は、百灯京コ！
The winner is Hyakki Kyoko!
やったあ！社長なのじゃ！私が社長です！
Yay! I'm the president! I'm the president!
社長は空いてるのじゃ？
The president's position is open, you say?
共同経営しよう！
Let's co-manage!
え、共同経営ってやっちゃダメって聞いたことあるのじゃ、破滅するって聞いたことあるのじゃやったら
Eh, co-management? I've heard you shouldn't do that, I've heard it ruins you if you do it.
トラブルの元を、そんな人間の営みまで聞いてしまってるのじゃ
The source of trouble, you've even listened to such human affairs, noicha!
はい、おめでとうございます！京子さんいかがですか、優勝されたお気持ち
Yes, congratulations! Kyoko-san, how do you feel about winning?
めちゃくちゃ嬉しいよこれ！
I'm so insanely happy about this!
なんかさ、クイズもすっごい楽しく回答させてもらって、で、億万長者になれて、最高の内閣だこれ、はあ！
Like, the quiz was so much fun to answer, and I became a trillionaire, this is the ultimate project, hah!
いや、京子のメタ読み力がすごかったね、ほんとに。すごくあった本当にね
Man, Kyoko's meta-reading ability was amazing, truly. It really was.
いやこれちょっと最後がちょっと10兆ポイント、いやあれか5000兆ポイントね、逃したのはちょっと惜しかったですけれど、それもねでも当りはついてましたから
Well, missing out on 10 trillion points at the very end—well, 5,000 trillion points—was a bit of a pity, but even so, she was on target,
いやもうこれはもうね、納得の優勝ということでしょ！
so this is definitely a well-deserved victory!
はいおめでとうございます！じゃあね、お待ちかねの商品の贈呈に移らさせていただきます
Yes, congratulations! Now then, let's move on to the presentation of the long-awaited prize!
こんな大きい額さ、なんかさ、税金とか大丈夫なのかな？
Such a big amount, like, won't taxes and stuff be okay?
ああ、そうか！確かに！贈与税的なね？
Ah, that's right! True! Gift tax-wise, right?
確かになんか半分ぐらい持ってくんじゃないの？
True, wouldn't they take about half?
確かにな、ま、そう税金とかね、その京子さんのほうでなんとかしてもろて、じゃあちょっと出たって
True. Well, taxes and stuff, Kyoko-san handles that somehow... wait, she laughed!
じゃあ行きましょう！賞金の贈呈、こちら！10兆ドルです！どどん！
Then let's go! Presentation of the prize money, here! 10 trillion dollars! Ta-da!
やったあ！やったのじゃ！やったあ！嬉しいの！いいなあ！
Yay! We did it, noicha! Yay! So happy! Awesome!
なんかこれ、え、ソピアのオリジナルダラってこと？
Is this Sopia's original dollar?
違う違う、あのこれ今ね画面には映せないからあれなんだけど、あのちゃんと本物のお札を用意してるから
No no, since we can't show it on screen right now, but we've prepared real bills,
そうじゃよね、うつせない、これガチガチのお札ですよ
That's right, can't show it, this is legit real bills.
でもさ、10兆っていうお札はないよね？
But like, there's no 10-trillion-dollar bill, right?
確かに。えー、するどいね。1兆っていうお札はないよね？うん。
True. Eh, sharp. There's no 1-trillion bill, right? Yeah.
いやあの、あるんですよこの世には。10兆ドルの札っていうのは。へえー、いい線ね、いい、勘の鋭さは嫌いじゃないよ
Well, there are in this world. 10-trillion-dollar bills. Heh, good line, good, I don't hate that sharp intuition.
なにこれ？何々？
What is this? What what?
えーとね、お札ってさ、人の顔が描いてあるんじゃろ？人の顔じゃないよ、なんか、雪だるまみたいなの描いてあるし。ナチスみたいな積まれてるんですけどね。はい、ということでこちら！
Um, bills have people's faces drawn on them, right? It's not a person's face, it's something like a snowman drawn on it. It's piled up like Nazis. Here it is!
10兆ジンバブエドルとなります！
It becomes 10 trillion Zimbabwean dollars!
ジンバブエかよ！
Zimbabwe?!
なにこれ！
What is this!
これさ、いくらなの？10兆ジンバブエドルって実際
Like, how much is this? 10 trillion Zimbabwean dollars actually?
ええとね、あの、最終的な為替レートで、大体日本円で数円くらいの価値
Uh, at the final exchange rate, it's worth around a few yen in Japanese yen.
円に換算できねえのじゃ！
You can't convert it to yen!
え？これライジャン？え、株式会社、株式会社社長社長、経営権経営権
Eh? Is this a lie? Eh, stock company, stock company, president president, management rights management rights...
ね、のっとるつもりだったのにね。
Hey, I was planning to take it over!
え？
Eh?
え、そっちは、もらえ、もらえないじゃん。
Wait, you can't get that side.
優勝ソッピアね、あの、十兆ドルって言っただけで何ドルかとか言ってないですからね。
Winning Soppia, you know, just said "10 trillion dollars" without specifying which currency.
いや、ペードルっつった。
No, she said pesos.
言ってない！言ってない！
She didn't! She didn't!
アーカイブだ！アーカイブ！
Check the archive! The archive!
決定される前に、聞いてたから！決定される前に！んー！
I heard it before it was decided! Before it was decided! Mmh!
フェイクに嘘にするな！はい、ということで。
Don't turn fake news into lies! Yeah, so...
あの、一応ね、一応本当にちゃんと、お札用意してきたので。
Uh, anyway, I actually prepared real banknotes, so...
ええと、こちら、一応ね、一応はあげるんですけど、あの、一応旧通貨なんでね、現在は通貨として使えないんで、まあコレクションアイテムとして。はい。
Um, I'm giving you this one, but since it's the old currency and can't be used as currency anymore, well, as a collection item. Yes.
え、それ普通に嬉しいかもしれない。
Wait, I might actually be really happy about that.
普通に十兆円欲しくない？
Wouldn't you normally want 10 trillion yen?
え、いいの？
Eh, really?
十兆円ってすごい。ちょっと嬉しい。
10 trillion yen is amazing. I'm kind of happy.
ちゃんとね、そう。だから一応、ちゃんと商品としては、ちゃんとソッピア的には優勝者にね、いいもの投げたいなって思ってちゃんと選んできたんですよ。
Right, yeah. So I wanted to pick something good as a prize for the winner from Soppia's perspective, so I carefully chose it.
ありがとー！
Thank you!
いーなー！いーなー！
So nice! So nice!
この十兆ジンバブエドルは、あの、イグノーベル賞のね、受賞者にも実際にこれが商品として送られてます。
This 10 trillion Zimbabwean dollar note is actually sent as a prize to the winners of the Ig Nobel Prize.
マジで！？
Seriously!?
そうなんだ！
Is that so!
そう、あのノーベル賞はね、あの、実際の、そう、実際のお金がもらえるんだけど、イグノーベル賞はパロディだから、そう、ジンバブエドルっていう。
Yeah, the Nobel Prize actually gives you real money, but since the Ig Nobel is a parody, it's Zimbabwean dollars.
へえー、すごい！
Whoa, amazing!
おもしろっ。
Interesting.
うん。
Yeah.
はーい、てことできゃちら、記念にお持ち帰りくださーい！
Alright, please take this home as a souvenir!
やったー！嬉しいー！
Yay! I'm so happy!
いーなー！受賞者と同じだ。
So nice! Same as the winner.
はーい、では、そろそろクイズイグノーベル賞はエンディングということで。
Alright, then, it's about time to wrap up Quiz! The Ig Nobel Prize.
最後にちょっと告知の方をね、させていただければと思います。
I'd like to make a few announcements at the end.
はい、ということで、こちら改めて遊びに行きたい、え、いろんなね、ものを出してます。まずはMV騒ぎぐるぐるタイム、みんな聞いてくれたかな？
Right, so we're releasing various things we want you to check out again. First, did everyone listen to the MV "Sawagi Guruguru Time"?
ぐるぐるぐるぐるタイムー、きめるのじゃー。
Guruguru Guruguru Time, I'll decide it.
こちらね、もういっぱいいっぱいみんな聞いてください。よろしくお願いします。
Please listen to this as much as possible, everyone. Thank you very much.
で、グッズやね、ボイスもたくさん出てるので、はい、グッズや、あと動く壁紙、スターティンボイスなどもみなさんね、ぜひぜひチェックしていただければと思います。
And there are lots of goods and voice packs out as well, so please be sure to check out the goods, moving wallpapers, and starting voice packs!
さらにさらに、あのメラッツとね、キョウコのカレンダーの、ほろかのね、デッキーもね、ね、もう10月、もうすぐね、発売されますし、ね、綴じの、おしほろめほろかもね、また12月かな？はい、デッキーもするのでこちらもぜひチェックしてください。
Furthermore, the calendar and "Horokan" deck featuring Meracchi and Kyoko will be released soon in October, and the bound "Oshi Horome Horoka" deck will also be out around December, so please check those out too!
あ、ソッピアも入ってるからね！ソッピアのサレヤ、スタートデッキにも入ってるからね！そうなんだ！サポートしますよ、みんなを、えい！むぎゃー！
Ah, Soppia is in there too! It's included in Soppia's Sareya starter deck! That's right! We'll support everyone, yay! Mgya!
で、あとね、ちょっともう時間始まっちゃっててあれなんだけれど、今、実はおしゃれまわりというのを1ドル企画がXの方で行われてます。
And also, the 1-dollar project "Oshare Mawari" is currently being held on X, even though time has already started.
そう、この後40分しかないんだけれど、もしよければ、はい、ちょっとね、Xの方でそのほろこみの、アカウントからちょっとね、あの、こういうルールでっていうのを見てもらって、もしよければ参加していただけると嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします。
Right, we only have 40 minutes left after this, but if you'd like, please take a look at the rules from Horokomi's account on X, and we'd be happy if you could participate. Thank you!
むぎゃー！はい、ということで改めてうちと遊び回りたい、今後ともどうぞよろしくお願いします。むぎゃー！
Mgya! Right, so we'd love to hang out with you again, and we appreciate your continued support. Mgya!
じゃあ、最後にみんなから一言ずつ感想をもらって終わりにしようかな。じゃあ、最初ま
Now, let's wrap up by getting a quick comment from everyone. First, is
いつか新社長になります！
Someday I'll become the new president!
野望がでかい！でっけえのじゃ！最強担当はだてじゃないぜのじゃ！
Such big ambitions! So huge! Being the strongest isn't just for show!
いやでもマジで今日楽しかった。本当にソッピアありがとー！
Seriously, today was really fun. Thank you so much, Soppia!
ありがと、ありがとう。
Thank you, thank you.
ではでは、続いてメラッチ。
Well then, next is Meracchi.
のじゃー！1問も当てられなかったけど、なかなかいい線いってたんじゃないのって思いますの。
Noja! I couldn't get a single question right, but I think I was pretty close.
いや、その考察すごい鋭かった、「あ、確かに」って思ったし。
Yeah, that deduction was super sharp, I thought "Ah, true".
そう、ぜひね、あの皿マンの尻尾でね、のずるはね、作ってみたいね。
Yeah, I'd definitely want to make a "nozuru" tail from Saraman.
面白いな、のじゃ。それよりなんか梅干しごみ、みんなで。
That's funny, noja. More importantly, everyone eating pickled plums together.
行きたい！パンツ埋める。いきたい。梅干しごみね。
I wanna go! Burying pants. I wanna go. Pickled plum trash.
いや本当にメラッチもありがとう！
Seriously, thank you too, Meracchi!
そしてラストは、綴り。
And last is Tsuzuri.
はーい、いや、惜しくも2位だったんですけどね、まあでも、え、面白かった！いろんな知識が増えてめっちゃ楽しかった。
Yes, well, I narrowly came in 2nd place, but you know, it was fun! I gained all sorts of knowledge and had a great time.
えー！嬉しい！え、すっごい真剣にあの解説聞きすぎて、なんか、え、頭良くなった気がする。
Eh! I'm so happy! Um, I listened so seriously to the explanations that I feel like my brain got smarter.
あれ？いま何言った、今の誰だ？いま何言ったの誰だ？
Huh? What did I just say? Who was that just now?
三人じゃね？うん。三人じゃね？全員です。うん。
Isn't it three people? Yeah. Three people? All of us. Yeah.
良くなったって思うんだけどな。でも今日の知識はしっかりと入れたからね。本当楽しかった、ソッピアありがとう！
I think I got better. But today's knowledge was firmly stored. It was really fun, thank you Soppia!
で、こちらこそ。いやでも本当に最後の靴下の考察とかかなりいい線いってたから、いやマジで綴り見込みあるよ。
And thank you too. Seriously, the final deduction about the socks was quite close, so Tsuzuri definitely has potential.
さあ、
Now,
虫次があったら優勝しよっかな、キョーコ。
If there's a next time, I'll win, Kyoko.
いや、ということでね、続編のね、今後の成長にも今後も期待ということで、
Anyway, with high hopes for the sequel's future growth,
改めてみんな本当にお疲れ、そしてね、本当にしてくれたね、
Once again, thank you all so much for your hard work, and...
リスナーのみんなもね、一緒に問題考えてくれたりね、もう本当に盛り上げてくれて本当にありがとう。
to all the listeners who helped think of questions and really hyped things up, thank you so much.
いや、本当にソピア、最後ちょっと感想言わせてもらうんですけど、
And Sopia, before I let you give your final thoughts,
いやマジでソピアね、リグノーブレッシュめっちゃ好きで。
seriously, Sopia, you love 'Rigne Oubliée' so much.
そう、めっちゃ面白くないって、そう毎年のね、すっげえ楽しみにしてたから、なんかそのね面白いリグノーブレッシュをこうやってみんなとね面白さ分かり合えたのが本当に嬉しくて。
Yeah, isn't it super fun? I've looked forward to it every year, so sharing the fun with everyone makes me so happy.
そう、だから改めてねもうみんな来てくれたみんなそしてねあの参加してくれた遊びたいのみんなに本当に本当に改めて感謝を申し上げたい本当ありがとう。
So, once again, I want to express my heartfelt thanks to everyone who came, participated, and wanted to play. Thank you so much.
こっちこそありがとう！
Thank you too!
こちらこそありがとう！
めちゃめちゃ楽しかった！
It was super fun!
マジ楽しかった。
It was really fun.
いやそう、めちゃめちゃ楽しかったよね。
Yeah, it really was.
やっぱ遊びたいのみんなすごいね、いろんなことに関心持ってくれるから、本当にソピアも話しててめっちゃ楽しいので、
And everyone at Asobitai is amazing, they get interested in all sorts of things, so talking with Sopia is always super fun.
本当に改めて遊びたい、もう最高最強だなってみたまた本当にありがとう。
Truly, Asobitai is the best and strongest, thank you so much again.
のじゃあ！のじゃあ！
Noja! Noja!
よかった！
Yay!
じゃあね、えっと最後挨拶で締めるね。その前に皆さん、
Well then, let's wrap up with final greetings. But before that, everyone,
あのチャンネル登録などお忘れの方いませんか概要欄に、はい、遊びたいのみんなのチャンネルやXのね、URLも
isn't there anyone who forgot to subscribe? In the description box, links to Asobitai's channels and X are also...
貼ってるので、もしまね
posted, so if you...
フォロー忘れてるよって方いたら忘れずにフォローお願いします。あと高評価もよければお願いします。
forgot to follow, please follow us. And likes are also appreciated if you'd like.
お願いしますのっちゃん！
Please, Nochan!
あれ？なんかメールハチ違う。
Huh? Wait, the mail batch is different.
ねぇ、何？フェイクニュースですのじゃって何？
Hey, what? 'Fake news, noja'? What's that?
え、いつの間にかこんなこと書かれてんだけど。コミュニティに書き留められてる。
Eh, since when was this written? It's pinned in the community.
うん。いやいやいや、実質、実質別に2位だし、ももももももも、いつそんなに2位って言ってるのじゃん。
Yeah. No no no, essentially, I'm 2nd place anyway, momomo... when did I say I'm 2nd?
じゃあ2位じゃん。
Then you're 2nd.
いや、めら3位だもん。
No, Mera's 3rd.
え？なんでそうなるのじゃ？
Eh? Why does it turn out that way?
ドデギリ靴、靴下パンチャつとしじい
Dodegiri shoes, socks pancha...
合ってないのじゃん。
That doesn't add up!
はい、まこれがね、あうちら遊び回りたいということで、
Right, well, this is... us wanting to hang out and play around,
ね、こんなわちゃわちゃ4人組ですが、今後ともどうぞよろしくお願いします。
you know, us four noisy folks, so please continue to support us.
では！よろしくお願いします！
Well then! Best regards!
お疲れ様でした！お疲れ様でした！
Good job! Good job!
いつもの挨拶で締めようかなと思います。みんな、最後の挨拶、みんなで「たい！」っていうのそろそろ大丈夫かな？
I think we'll wrap up with our usual greeting. Everyone, are we ready to say 'Tai!' together?
いくよー！
Here we go!
もちろん！
Of course!
おっ、じゃあ行きましょう！いくよ！
Alright, let's go! Here we go!
次も遊び回ろう！たい！
Let's hang out and play again next time! Tai!
ありがとう！でわでわ、まったねー！
Thank you! Well then, see you later!
バイバイ！まったねー！
Bye-bye! See you!